<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sounding of the last trumpet or, Several visions, declaring the universall overturning and rooting up of all earthly powers in England. With many other things foretold, which shall come to passe in this year, 1650. / Lately shewed unto George Foster, who was commanded to print them.</title>
            <author>Foster, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84731</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E616_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215474</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871448</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165764</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84731)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165764)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E616[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sounding of the last trumpet or, Several visions, declaring the universall overturning and rooting up of all earthly powers in England. With many other things foretold, which shall come to passe in this year, 1650. / Lately shewed unto George Foster, who was commanded to print them.</title>
                  <author>Foster, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In this edition line ornament consists of 6 large ornaments, 5 small ones, and the letter "S".</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Novemb: 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165764:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SOVNDING OF THE LAST TRUMPET OR Severall Viſions, declaring the univerſall overturning and rooting up of all Earthly Powers in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> With many other things foretold, which ſhall come to paſſe in this Year, 1650.</p>
            <p>Lately ſhewed unto GEORGE FOSTER, who was commanded to Print them.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165764:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165764:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O Earth, earth, earth, hear the word of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>tremble</hi> thou earth, <hi>at the preſence of the mighty God of</hi> Iacob; <hi>for behold, he comes to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on his enemies,</hi> and they that have exerciſed oppreſsion ſhall be by the <hi>All of all, things</hi> confounded and brought to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whether they be outward <hi>powers</hi> that have their fellow creatures <hi>in bondage to them, or the powers of fleſh,</hi> ruling and domineeering in <hi>them,</hi> Iſay both <hi>powers</hi> ſhall be brought to nothing, and ſhall not be able to ſtand any longer; for his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty appearing in brightneſſe, will be a terrour to all <hi>fleſh</hi> and all <hi>powers</hi> ſhall become as weak as water before him; and <hi>Lucifer</hi> that hath made the <hi>Nations to tremble,</hi> ſhall be brought to nothing, even all the <hi>power, ſtrength and glory of man</hi> ſhall be but as <hi>graſſe, and as the flower of the field that is ſoon cut down, and then comes to nothing, and is as if it were not;</hi> even ſo at the appearing of the Lord of hoſts, ſhall all powers of what ſort or under what notion ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever be, in a very little while, <hi>as if they were not,</hi> and <hi>God alone,</hi> even the eternall God appeare to be King and Lord over all the Earth; at whoſe appearance all things beſides himſelfe ſhall be brought to nothing, even all <hi>POWERS</hi> ſhall become as nothing: and the <hi>mighty</hi> men, and <hi>great</hi> men, as <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> for fear of the Lord of Hoſts, <hi>ſhall run into the holes of the rocks, and into the Dennes of the Earth to hide themſelves for fear of his Majeſty, for he doth now ariſe to ſhake terribly the earth, and all the earth</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:165764:3"/> 
               <hi>ſhall become dung before him;</hi> and all the <hi>powers</hi> of the earth ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be as dung before his Inſtruments whom he hath made choice of, to do his great and terrible <hi>work:</hi> for he hath now a <hi>ſtrange work</hi> to do which will not be done by the <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of the earth; but the mighty <hi>Jehovah</hi> will do his ſtrange work by po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, weak, and diſpiſed inſtruments, even by thoſe that are as nothing in themſelves, that the <hi>All of al things</hi> may appear to be their power and their ſtrength, and ſo through the <hi>ſtength</hi> of the <hi>mighty God, levell and lay mountaines and hils low, and make plaines n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d vallies equall with them:</hi> add ſo I will leave you to the enſuing Treatiſe, there to ſee what Gwd hath purpoſed to do: the which he hath been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reveale to me by <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſions,</hi> which <hi>power</hi> as I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a creature ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſo powerfully appeared in me, as I have not been able to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,</hi> but muſt ſend it forth th the publike view, as being one that that been made for a <hi>figne and wohder amongſt men,</hi> and ſo for my own puietneſſe ſake, and qeace of <hi>Spirit,</hi> I am made to put it to thy view, and ſo am contented to be a <hi>foole,</hi> and to undergo the hard and harſh cenſures of many, leaveing it to thy ſerious conſideration, or to thy malicious <hi>ſpirit,</hi> which may <hi>bite</hi> againſt it, and ſay I am deluded, and the Devil hath power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me: I'le leave it to you that ſee or heare of it; <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time to make manifeſt what it is,</hi> and I'le wait <hi>upon the mighty God of Jacob,</hi> being confident he hath made out himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me by <hi>Viſion</hi> and <hi>Revelation;</hi> and hath ſet me as a <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in the eyes of men: but <hi>wonder</hi> not as to mock and laugh at me leaſt your hearts be hardned, &amp; ſo you be one of the veſſels whom the Lord will <hi>powre out the fiercenes of his wrath upon;</hi> for ſurely my God hath not ſet me as a <hi>ſign</hi> for nothing; if he hath, I am contented to be nothing, <hi>that he,</hi> the Lord of hoſts, <hi>may appear to be all:</hi> yea, I am confident the <hi>All of all things</hi> hath a very great work to do, &amp; he hath made uſe of me, as of one that am a <hi>poor creature,</hi> purpoſely to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t me a ſign, for
<pb facs="tcp:165764:3"/> ſome to be <hi>forewarned that the Lord of hoſts is comming to deſtroy all things beſide himſelfe;</hi> that they may be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling when he appeareth <hi>to forſake all,</hi> and to count that which for the preſent is <hi>their God,</hi> as gold and ſilver, as nothing <hi>that they may cloath and feed the hungry,</hi> and ſo eſcape the day <hi>that ſhall burne as an Oven.</hi> But for others to be a <hi>ſtone of ſtumbling; a gin and ſnare at which they ſhall ſtumble and fall.</hi> And ſo <hi>Reader</hi> that thou maiest underſtand by reading of this treatiſe what God is now a doing: and how powerfull he is. For I have ſeen him to be very ſtrong, for theſe things following; I did much question whether they were not a deluſion of the Devill, by reaſon of the ſtrangeneſſe of them, &amp; ſo did by queſtioning of them bring my ſelfe into a reſtleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: as ſeverall times to be tempted to make away my ſelfe. <hi>For theſe things</hi> ſaith the tempter, <hi>if thou publiſh them will make you a hiſſing and a laughing ſtock:</hi> and fleſh being willing to be at eaſe, I could have bin contented to have buried them in the bed of oblivion, &amp; ſo thought to have hid them and not to have brought them forth, but the voice of the Lord came to me ſaying, <hi>that thou maieſt know that I the Lord of hoſts,</hi> I <hi>have made out unto the by viſion, &amp; revealed things that ſhall ſurely come to paſſe, &amp; that I have commanded thee to put them in print, &amp; therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to go to</hi> London, <hi>thou ſhalt be dumb</hi> (and ſo I was for ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houres) <hi>as a token to convince thee</hi> of <hi>thy unbeliefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the next day, the voice of the Lord ſaid I ſhould be blind, as a token to convince me of my unbeliefe, which I was for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven houres. And at the ſame time, the voice of the Lord ſaid: (for to haſten me away for to be a <hi>wonder in London)</hi> I ſhould be deprived of the uſe of my <hi>hand</hi> untill I did go up to ſpeak with <hi>Fairfax;</hi> and being thus taken <hi>ſpeechles</hi> and <hi>blind</hi> and my <hi>right hand cloſed up,</hi> that I could not open it; I'did come up to <hi>London,</hi> and being in <hi>London I</hi> did go to the <hi>Generals</hi> houſe for to ſpeak with him, but could not, then I
<pb facs="tcp:165764:4"/> went againe, and could not; and the third time; but could not be admitted for to ſpeak with him: And all this while my <hi>hand was cloſed up</hi> ſo faſt that ſeverall that ſaw it did not conclude it was by a ſupernaturall power: and I did tell them that I had a meſſage to deliver to the Generall: but for the preſent I knew not what it was but I never did tell any that it could not be opened by force and ſtrength: but did tell them that <hi>I my ſelfe could not open it:</hi> but as ſoon as I did ſpeak with the Generall it ſhould open, which was now ſo cloſed for a <hi>ſigne to convince me of my unbeliefe,</hi> and alſo <hi>a ſtumbling-block for thoſe that did by violence open it;</hi> as a Prieſt for one, who was the chief cauſe of it, I being then in the Generalls houſe intending for to have ſpoken with him, as to deliver to him what God ſhould have made out to me. But I ſee it ſince to be the wiſdome of my God that I did not ſpeak with him, and likewiſe the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of God <hi>that my hand was opened by violence,</hi> that it may prove the fall of the enemies of <hi>Sion,</hi> and give them cauſe to <hi>mock</hi> and <hi>laugh</hi> at me; that ſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y may be <hi>for the ſlaughter</hi> when the Lord ariſeth <hi>to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke the earth terribly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> becauſe I would not have you wonder why I do not go to the Generall for to ſpeake with him, and ſo conclude that I am deluded, as they that open<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d my hand did; for the <hi>wayes of God are paſt finding out,</hi> and my meſſage is done for the preſent in that I have endeavoured for to ſpeak with him, and I am as much ſatisfied with my condition as if I had ſpoke with him, for I ſee an over-ruling <hi>power</hi> and ſo am made for to wait upon that <hi>power</hi> that made all creatures (knowing that he will do his pleaſure) untill he doth in a more powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>full manner carry me forth in ſuch a way to act, which as I am a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I am dead to, and when he appeares in power in his own time for to make uſe of me or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any other of his creatures, they ſhall not be able to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hſtand him, as I f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r my own pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t have not beene able to withſtand. So with this caution to you all, not to
<pb facs="tcp:165764:4"/> mock at me leſt you mock not only me, but <hi>the All of all things,</hi> and ſo daſh your ſelves againſt that rock which will beat to pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all other powers beſides himſelfe that he may <hi>be all and in all,</hi> I am willing to be ſilent, leaving my God to do with me, and all creatures, what he pleaſeth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEORGE FOSTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:165764:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165764:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>January</hi> 14 1650.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt day of the appearing of the eternall God in me, ſo as to make his excellent Majeſty moſt illuſtriouſly to ſhine in me as the moſt excellent and moſt glorious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, was by declaring himſelf to be my God, and that he was come to make himſelfe known unto me; who had a long time been in me buried under the clouds of proud fleſh, and I was ignorant of him, and though I was ignorant of him [of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God dwelling in me] yet he did dwell in me, and was the life of me, which is a great myſtery, and vnknown to moſt creatures, though moſt profeſſe they know God, that God, even the eternall God dwels in them, by which <hi>they live and move and have their being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it hath pleaſed the infinite Iehovah [who is the fulneſſe of all, and fills the Creation with his grace] to appeare moſt gloriouſly in me, ſtripping and robbing me of all my former glory, that he alone may appear to be my all and in all, and ſo to declare and make himſelfe manifeſt to me, that he the eternall God doth dwell in me, and is the life of me, and that he will no longer be buried in me, but now will ariſe like a man of warre, tearing and deſtroying all proud fleſh which hath covered him, that he alone may appear to be my eternall King, and ſo to take me up into the full injoyment of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by declaring in me, ſaying, I the Lord of hoſts am come, which voice was the moſt joyfulleſt voice that ever ſounded in mine eares, though it was a terrour to my fleſh, yet <hi>I</hi> may ſay with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>this is the day which the Lord hath made, come let us be glad and rejoyce in it.</hi> The Prophet was not ignorant that the Lord did make all the dayes, for he knew well enough the Lord did make all, but this day wherein he ſayes, he will rejoyce; was that day, even that day as the eternall God did appeare to be his God; and ſo apprehending him ſelfe by the manifeſtations of God to him, to be one with God, and no longer at a diſtance from God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, did cauſe him to rejoyce and be glad.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:165764:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But who ſhall abide the day of his coming? or who ſhall be able to ſtand when he appeareth?</hi> Surely no fleſh ſhall be able to ſtand in that body when the mighty God of <hi>Jacob</hi> appeareth, neither ſhall any fleſh abide there, neither ſhall that creature in whom he is pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf, be able to oppoſe him, for the Lord will do all his pleaſure; <hi>He is like a refiners fire, and fullers ſop.</hi> The eternall God by his bright appearing in his ſons, he will purifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine them, by deſtroying that which hath troubled them, and hath kept them at a diſtance from him, and cauſe them to ſee <hi>evill no more,</hi> and to ſee <hi>former things to paſſe away, and all things become new:</hi> And thus it hath pleaſed my excellent Majeſtie who dwels in me, to make known himſelf unto me, that ſo J may ſee former things, <hi>or old things paſſe away, and all things become new:</hi> And as the eternal God caught <hi>Paul</hi> up into rhe third heaven, and he heard there <hi>words not fit to be uttered;</hi> becauſe if he ſhould have made them know, they could not underſtand them, by reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of diſpenſations wherein they lived, <hi>Paul</hi> being a father, &amp; all they babes and children. So my excellent Majeſty the eternall God, having taken me up into himſelfe by his appearing in me in ſuch a high diſcovery of his love unto me, as to make me ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in me, and I to have no life but he to be my all; yea, my life, and that I can do nothing without him, who hath cauſed me to deliver my Kingdome, all my ſtrength [he being now the end of it] to my Father, that he may be <hi>all</hi> and in <hi>all:</hi> yea he hath [even my eternall God] ſo powerfully overcom me, that whether I was wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or no, deſtroyed my fleſh (for <hi>God is a conſuming fire)</hi> that he may take the kingdom to himſelfe, and ſo to <hi>be all, and in all in me:</hi> even thus it pleaſed my eternall God even in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye to ſtrike me dead, and likewiſe to raiſe me from the dead; and to cauſe me to heare the Angell ſound the laſt Trumpet, and ſo to take me up to meet the Lord in the aire, and ſo to be ever with the Lord, ſounding the tune of the ſeven Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets alwayes in mine ears, and cauſing me to hear the noiſe of the laſt trumpet, even the myſtery of God, ſaying, <hi>it is done, it is done, and time ſhall be no longer;</hi> making me to <hi>ſee ſeventy weeks,</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Daniel,</hi> to be at one end, and ſo to ſee <hi>ſin and tranſegreſſion to be finiſhed,</hi> and to hear a voice within me, ſaying, <hi>everlaſting righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is brought in:</hi> This is that voice which hath already ſhoke the earth, <hi>but yet once more</hi> (ſaith my excellent Majeſty, who doth moſt gloriouſly ſhin in me) that he wil <hi>ſhake not only the earth again</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:165764:6"/> 
               <hi>but the heavens alſo:</hi> for it is not the worke of God onely to deſtroy the earthly powers and to bring them to nothing, though he will do it, but he will alſo deſtroy the heavenly powers, even that welfavoured har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot: even thoſe that thinke themſelves to be <hi>Iews and are not,</hi> as well Independency and Baptiſme way as he hath done Epiſcopacy and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie, and ſo to bring all fleſh in to confuſion, and to deſtroy the wiſdome of man <hi>that he alone may be exalted,</hi> and then wil the lord <hi>make a way in the wilderneſſe, and pathes in the deſarts. for to give water unto his people.</hi> And when the Lord hath done this great work, as he will do, to cauſe the poor creatures as think themſeves as lights and ſtars, and have taught otheres, to be nothing but in confuſion, then will they appear to be the wilderneſs and deſarts barren and empty; and that nothing will ſatisfie them but the powring of the ſpirit from on high, which is no other, but God appearing in them, and making himſelf known to them that he dwels in them, which dwelling in them will be as water of life unto them, and ſo will the Propheſies be fulfilled; I <hi>will do a new thing,</hi> which new thing willbe the depriving of the creature of all his ſelfe-righteouſneſſe or holineſte, and will make him to ſay, in the Lord <hi>have I righteouſneſſe,</hi> which righteouſneſſe will be God alone appearing to be the <hi>old way,</hi> and ſo will make them <hi>hear a voice behind them ſaying, this is the old way walke in it</hi> O the abundance of joy that is contained in theſe words: O it is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Ioy which the Apoſtle mentions, to hear God Preaching and ſpeaking to us, yea, in us: what a deale of labour will this ſave poor creatures, this will ſtay them from running to <hi>broken ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns that can hold no water,</hi> this will take them off from Idolizing Prieſts, when the voice of God ſpeaks in us behould, this is the myſterie that is to be made manifeſt to the ſons of <hi>Sion</hi> in theſe later dayes, <hi>Chriſt in them the hope of glory,</hi> that ſo in ſeeing God in them, and they to <hi>be in God, are the new jeruſalem that is com out of heauen,</hi> and ſo are the gueſts of that joyful wedding, hearing thoſe joyful w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rds, <hi>the mariage of the Lamb is ready,</hi> and ſo looſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be married to the eternal God, and they to be the Lambs wife, and ſo by the power of the eternal God dwelling in them, they overcome and do inherit all things, by being brought into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God, and ſo inherit all things in God; for God being theirs, all things are theirs, <hi>whether things preſent or things to come ſo</hi> that they ſhall now ſee weeping and ſorrow to be fled away, and ſo to go with everlaſting ſongs to <hi>Sion,</hi> in ſinging and dancing to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165764:7"/> the houſe, of the Lord; Beloved this is that feaſt of fat things upon the mountaine, wine upon the leaves, even God the eternall King dwelling and manifeſtling himſelfe to you as he hath done to me, whereby I ſee by the excellent Majeſtie, the eternal God in me, that crooked wayes are now made ſtreight, and rough places made ſmooth; high places made low, and low places made high; fleſh brought to nothing, and God to be all and in all; all my life joy and ſtrength, and ſo no longer to labour and travell with child, but to bring forth, or declare that this eternall God is in me; and that he hath manifeſted himſelfe unro me, in a more extraordinary manner then ever before he did which extraordinary manner was as followeth.</p>
            <p>As <hi>I</hi> lay awake in my bed between three and foure a clock in the morning <hi>Ian.</hi> 14. 1650. the Lord cauſed me to heare a pleaſant fit of muſick or melody, which muſick made me much admire, being ſo early in the morning, and one being with me I would faine have ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him if he heard or knew where it was; But as J was thinking to know where it was, <hi>I</hi> was taken in a ſtrange manner, with tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſhaking; burning, and groaning, which made the party which lay with me much wonder and ſpeak to me, but J could not make him any anſwer. And after J had lain trembling and groaning [be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of paine within and without] for halfe an houre and upwards: J began to have abundance of inward joy and conſolation, even ſo full of joy was J that I was not able to containe my ſelfe, or expreſſe that comfort I had within me; but J did at length break forth in laugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, ſo heartily that I ſcarce ever laughed ſo heartily before, and did utter theſe words, the Lord of hoſts is come, and the moſt joyfull day that ever came is now, and no joy like unto this joy: and then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was J taken with trembling and Groaned as I did before; and then afterwards I brake forth with laughing, and thus <hi>I</hi> did for foure times in the morning uſeing, the ſame expreſſions as J did at firſt: all this while beholding nothing with my outward eyes: for they were ſhut up that J could ſcarce open them, but beheld a glorious object within mee, which made me much rejoyce; and ſo I continued ſometimes rejoycing within my ſelfe, and ſometimes full of trouble, untill about twelve a clock at noon. And then was I taken in the ſame manner as before, and had three more fits; and in the laſt of the three, I being filled more with joy then in any of the reſt; J lifted up my hands and cryed out, the Lord of hoſts is come: And it is done, it is done, being ſo filled with joy as if it was the moſt joyfulls
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:165764:7"/> newes which ever came to me; which ſince I have found it to be and that never no joy was like this joy to me, if I may ſpeake the truth and lie not. And afterwards I paſſed the day and night, ſometimes being full of joy, and ſomtimes full of ſorrow; and the next day being thurſday, J paſſed that with joy and went to bed, finding my ſelf prittie well ſatisfied (but not quite ſatisfied) and ſlept a while, but awaked about 2. a clock; and being awake I was much troubled in my ſelf and perplexed in my minde, but at length <hi>I</hi> heard a voice within me ſaying, heare my voice; and <hi>I</hi> cried out, who art thou that I ſhould heare? and <hi>I</hi> was anſwered with theſe words, I am the Lord of hoſts the holy one of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and I was preſently, yea, of an inſtant taken with ſhaking and groaning; and being tormented in my minde; <hi>I</hi> then heard a voice ſaying to me, I am now come to torment thee, to conſume and burn thee up to nothing; and I did then apprehend a bundance of miſerie and ſorrow, crying out <hi>I</hi> was in hel: &amp; preſently <hi>I</hi> was as ful of joy in apprehending a glorious God within me, which made me as much rejoyce &amp; laugh within my ſelf, as if I had bin in no miſerie at all. yea, though I was in hel, &amp; among all the Devils, <hi>I</hi> cryed out, ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flie away. Some 5, or 6. of theſe fits, in my miſerie, I cryed out I was in hel. In my joy I cryed out, the Lord of hoſts is come: and ſorrow and ſighing will now flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and that the Lord of hoſts will not ſhake the earth, but the heavens alſo. Theſe fits being over; there did appear to me four black horſes all in harneſſe, drawing and tugging as if they had bin in a cart that was ſet, and ſtrived harder then ordinary to get out: And <hi>I</hi> ſaid Lord, what is the meaning of this (ſighing and groaning untill <hi>I</hi> had an anſwer) and I was anſwered, that theſe do repreſent the powers of the world that do oppoſe God in his people, &amp; all powers [that they are now ready to be drawn in pieces and theſe being vaniſhed: There appeared four horſes al' read, and I ſaid Lord what is the meaning of this, and the Lord ſaid, theſe do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent all powers to be in blood readie to be ſtrangled: and theſe being gone, there appeared 4. pale horſes like unto death (for J looked much upon them) for they looked very pale, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they did brance up and down and kept a vaporing about. But preſently death ſeized upon them, and <hi>I</hi> beheld till <hi>I</hi> ſaw all powers throwne down, and covered in the earth that they ſhould riſe no more. And after theſe 4. pale horſes were covered under the earth, there appeared one white horſe without ſpot or ſtaine, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165764:8"/> one upon him all in glory, having a ſword in his hand, and he rid from Eaſt to Weſt &amp; from North to South, and he ſaid, <hi>the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world are becom the kingdoms of the Lord, &amp; he doth raign</hi> &amp; Iſaid Lord, what doth this mean? and the Lord ſaid, That I the eternall God will appeare ſo glorious in my people to the burning up of fleſh and ſin, that they ſhall appear Conquerours and Kings; and I the Lord God am and will appear to be all and in all to my people. And as he prances from Eaſt to Weſt from North to South, without any let or hinderance: ſo ſhall my people live in the injoyment of me; and nothing ſhall make them afraid, and a little while after, I beheld an Angell coming from God and have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his hand abook, and it was open. And he came to me and bid me put forth my hand and take it, and eat it and I did put forth my hand and did take it, and (I ſaid) Lord what means this, and my God ſaid that this is a teſtimonie or a ſeal to you that I am come to you, and have put my law in your heart, and have writ it in your inward parts, and you ſhall ſin no more; and I was made to bow ſeven times to this Angell and my father ſaid, even ſo ſhall all fleſh bow to me in my people: and as the book was open in his hand, it ſhews that the myſterie which hath bin his is now to be made manifeſt and the everlaſting Goſpel to be preached.</p>
            <p>And on the thurſeday morning between 5. and 6. a clok, I was taken with trembling and horror, and was ſtrook dead for a while ſo as I drew no breath at all, and at length I heard a great roaring of waters, which made a great noiſe, and when I came to my ſelfe, I groaned, and ſighed, and ſaid, Lord, what means this noiſe, and my excellent majeſtie which dwell in me, ſaid, that as you heare the roaring of waters and none is able to ſtill the noiſe? ſo ſhall my people, even my ſons come with ſinging and rejoycing to Sion and none ſhall make them weep any more: hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, I was much taken with joy even overcome with joy, and continued full of joy I was taken as I was before, and my breath being gone from me again. I lay as dead for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while; And did at length ſee a company of men and women ſtanding upon <hi>Sion,</hi> having harpes, and made muſick; and then came ſome others and they danced; and there was one more glorious then the reſt in the midſt of them. And I beheld till he that was in the midſt of them did go into them all and they became all as one.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165764:8"/>
            <p>And on Friday morning about five or ſix a clock, I was taken with horrour and feare, and was much perplexed (in my ſelfe) in mind and at length J heard a voice, ſaying, <hi>heare me, and obſerve what</hi> I <hi>ſay and write: That as</hi> I <hi>have tormented and plagued thee, ſo will</hi> I <hi>torment &amp; plague all powers beſides my ſelfe:</hi> And J ſaid, Lord, wilt thou torment and deſtroy this Parliament? and the Lord ſaid J <hi>will deſtroy and conſume and bring to nothing the Parliament &amp; all power that have exerciſed cruelty upon my people; &amp; will give the glory, and honour and ſtrength of Kingdomes to my people, that there may be univerſall liberty and freedom, and will make the Wolfe and the Lamb lie down together, and be at peace one with another; and as you did ſee a white horſe, and one upon him all in glory the night before laſt night, with a ſword in his hand, riding from Eaſt to Weſt, and from North to South and none to oppoſe him and none to help him but that he did deſtroy all his enemies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: So I will (even by my own power and by my ſpirit) bring to nothing all the glory, honour, and power of all fleſhly powers that J alone may be and none beſides me,</hi> And J ſaid, Lord, how long will it be firſt? and the Lord ſaid, in a very little while, and J will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, overturne, overturne, and will appear in my Temple to the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of mine own work.</p>
            <p>And on the 25. of <hi>January</hi> in the night, J was taken in the ſame manner as before, but only my fit of trouble was leſn'd and my fit of laughter more then any J had before: and after my mirth was over J was cauſed to lie ſtill. And J heard a voice of very great waters, which made me greeve within my ſelfe, untill I had an anſwer what they ſhould meane or what the noiſe ſhould ſignifie.</p>
            <p>And at length my God within me told me, that the waters doth ſignifie the perſons of <hi>Sion</hi> ſinging and rejoycing in <hi>Sion;</hi> and as the noiſe of the waters was great, ſo ſhould the joy and gladneſſe of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> be great, and as I heard a noiſe and did not know from whence it came; ſo ſhould their joy and gladneſſe come from God, within them and not from Creature objects. And I ſaid Lord they rejoyce and ſing allready; but my eternall God within me told me, that their joy now is mixt with ſorrow, and ſo is not perfect joy. But they ſhall ere long be brought into a full enjoyment of me, and then ſhall ceaſe from ſorrow.</p>
            <p>And preſently after J beheld two Armies of men, one coming out of the North, and the other out of the South a little Weſtward. And the leader of them that came out of the South did ſeeme to be a very ſolentary man, and the other leader a fierce man, and J
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165764:9"/> beheld till they met one another, and had a ſharp bout of fighting one at the other. But at length the horſe belonging to thoſe that came out of the South (there being one very glorious amongſt them) broke in amongſt the foote and routed them and tooke their General, and ſo had the diſpoſing of the Field; and marched away preſently to <hi>London,</hi> and ſearched a great houſe; pulling thoſe that were in it out of it. And I ſaid Lord what meaneth this? and the Lord ſaid. That theſe be my inſtruments to deſtroy all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and to bring to nothing thoſe that are in power. And ſo to take the Kingdomes of this world, and to give them to the Saints. And moreover the Lord ſaid, that theſe his inſtruments by which he hath done this, he will ſo overpower that they ſhall not be like others, as to be a ſelf ſeeking people (no) but he will make them to be bright. <hi>That there may be no complainings in our ſtrees.</hi> And ſo reſtore the creation from the bondage it now groans under, into the Glorious liberty of the ſons of God. That there may be univerſal liberty and freedome; and moreover the Lord ſaid: that the faſhion of this world goeth out, or is now a deſtroying; and that the men of this world ſhall now uſe it as if they uſed it not; and that I will (ſaith the Lord) make thoſe that have riches diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearſe them abroad. That that ſaying may come to paſſe, and that my inſtruments by which I will do theſe things, ſhall confeſs that it is not by power or ſtrength of men; but that it is God that is in them that doth theſe things. And ſo ſhall wholly deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from uſurping a power over others as to make Lawes for others to walke by. But as <hi>I</hi> have taken the power to my ſelf, ſo ſhall they leave me (ſaith my God) to do what <hi>I</hi> ſee good to all people; and my worke will be (ſaith God) to bring in univerſal libertie. And I ſaid how long Lord? And the Lord ſaid, within a moneth or a very little while, and it ſhall come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>And in a little while after <hi>I</hi> ſaw a company of men and women ſinging and dancing, and they had every one of them a booke open in their right hand. And <hi>I</hi> ſaid, Lord what meaneth this? and my eternal God within me ſaid. That theſe repreſent my ſons and daughters that ſhall ſing and dance in <hi>Sion,</hi> and go up to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the houſe of the Lord with everlaſting joy: and as they had every one of them a book open in their hands: it ſets forth that the myſterie which hath bin hid, is now by me (ſaith the Lord) made manifeſt, even Chriſt within them. And ſo ſhall be as my Thundering Angels crying out <hi>it is done, it is done, and time</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:165764:9"/> 
               <hi>ſhall be no more</hi> (ſaith my God) <hi>and ſo ſhall ſe tranſgreſſion finiſhed, &amp; everlaſting righteouſneſs brought in.</hi> And all things with them to become new; former things be paſſed away. And ſo to be married to me the Lord: to be one with me. God living in them and they in God; and indeed are the <hi>new Jeruſalem that comes out of heaven, and the Tabernacle of God with men.</hi> Theſe fits being over, I was wrappped up in ſilence for a while: And the condition that I was in afterwards, was not a condition of horror, of trouble or feare, for about three nights before this, <hi>I</hi> heard a voice within me ſay, I am come, and will declare unto you, and <hi>I</hi> did waite for to have ſome thing from my God (by the working of my ſpirit within me) which having now, I was taken in a moſt pleaſant manner, &amp; was forced to lie ſinging &amp; whiſling; and then to riſe out of my bed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one and two a clock for to dance I and ſo continued ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; dancing neare upon two hours by the clock, ſinging in this manner as followeth, or the expreſſions which <hi>I</hi> uſed ſome of them I wil here relate, though <hi>I</hi> am not able to remember a quarter of them. The King, the everlaſting King, the King of glory comes; <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah, Halelujah, Halelujah, the Lord God omnipotent reignes: Sing, ſing, be glad O Sion! for behold thy King, the everlaſting King, the King of glory comes: ſhout, ſhout O Sion for behold thy King, the holy, one of Iſrael is in the midſt of thee; &amp; thou ſhalt ſe ſorrow no more: now ore the kingdoms of this world becomthe kingdoms of the Lord, &amp; of his Chriſt, &amp; he ſhal reigne for ever. Sing, ſing, and rejoyce for behold thou ſhalt no longer have neede of the ſun of moon to give thee light,</hi> that is, outward ordinances, no but ſaith the Lord, <hi>I</hi> wil be thy light &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Sing &amp; rejoyce, &amp; go up with joy &amp; rejoycing to the mountain of the houſe of the Lord; for now ſhal the light of the moon be as the light of the ſun. &amp; the light of the ſun ſhal be ſeven fold more now then hath bin. Shout and be glad, for behold, I come; and he that is weake and feeble amongſt you ſhal be as David, &amp; David ſhal be as the Angel of God, even as God:</hi> Sing &amp; rejoyce, for behold you ſhal now ſay, <hi>this is the Lord our God we have waited for him,</hi> and he is now come; <hi>therefore let us be glad and rejoyce in his Salvation. Sing and rejoyce and be glad, for now the tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them: Shout, ſhout, crie aloude, ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet. And ſay unto Sion, thy King cometh:</hi> prepare, prepare, make ready, the marriage of the Lamb is now come. <hi>For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> I <hi>come as a bride adorned for her husband.</hi> Sing and rejoyce for now Jeruſalem cometh out of heaven: and former things ſhall paſſe away, and now ſhall all things become new: Sing and make ready,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165764:10"/> for the marriage of the Lamb is come: Shout and be glad for the water of life doth now appeare for to heale the Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crie. Crie, what ſhall</hi> I <hi>crie? Crie all fleſh is graſs, the graſs wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the flower fades and comes to nothing, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od abides for ever:</hi> Crie, Crie, the ſpirit of the Lord blowes upon fleſh, that ſo fleſh may come to nothing: I <hi>have a long time holden my peace and have bin ſtill, but now will I ariſe (ſaith the Lord) like a man of war and will teare and devoure in pieces and none ſhall deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now will <hi>I</hi> appeare to be (ſaith the Lord) the ſtone cut out of the mountaine: Crie, crie, what ſhall <hi>I</hi> crie? the Lord of Hoſts will overthrow the ſtrength of Kingdomes. And will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be an Iron rod that ſhall breake in pieces all powers like a potters veſſel. And will make every one to throw their Idols of Gold and Silver away: money which men have made Idols of, ſhall now by the bright appearing of God, be counted nothing, but ſhal be thrown from one unto the other: And they that have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance ſhall hide themſelves for feare of the Lord of Hoſts. Theſe and ſuch like expreſſions by way of ſinging I did utter: and why <hi>I</hi> count it ſinging, is becauſe I did (as being overpowered with joy) crie <hi>ha ha tall toll lall derah la loll la dero tall derall tall toll dero tall aroll atoll loll loll dero,</hi> in ſuch a way I did breake forth between every 4. lines I have writ or oftner.</p>
            <p>And on the 29. day of the ſame month about 7. a clock in the night I ſaw in a viſion two armies of men one a coming againſt the other; the ſame Leaders that were in the viſion before, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt two armies mentioned, &amp; I beheld til they were drawn up in a body, ſeeing their drums beating and their collours flying; their muſquets charged, and the ſouldiers with lighted matches in their hands: and I beheld till J ſaw that theſe two armies did meet, and the muſqueteers fired and fell off, and J ſaw men ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times drap down: But at length J ſaw the Generals horſe (which came out of the South) break in amongſt their enemies and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly routed them, and tooke the General and killed him, and ſo had the field to themſelves. And J ſaid Lord, what is the meaning of this? and my eternall God within me told me. That the General and his armie that came out of the South, are inſtruments which J have choſen to do my worke: and the other Generall and his Souldiers are for the Parliament: and J beheld til the General that overcame marched with all his armie to <hi>London,</hi> and entred the Citie, and went to the Parliament-houſe. But they were diſperſed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165764:10"/> and I ſaw the General and his Officers ſit as a Parliament in the roome of the other, and did promiſe that they would now reſtore freedome to the people: and I ſaw the General and his Officers go into the Halls where money was and threw it to the Souldiers, and the Souldiers had ſo much, that they gave it away to the poore; and I heard the poore ſay one unto the other, theſe are joyfull daies.</p>
            <p>And I deſired the ſubſtance of it and it is this (as my Lord hath revealed it to me) That the General and the people with him are the inſtruments of God. And he hath choſen them for to beat in pieces all powers; and to threſh mountaines and hills to chaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that they may be no longer: and ſo to give the power to them that they may (or God in them) reſtore England from bondage: and by their giving of money away ſo freely, it ſhewes that the time is now come, that the Lord will redeeme the creation from bondage, and that <hi>I</hi> will (ſaith God) ſo breake that domineering ſelf that hath bin in man: That he ſhall now throw away his Idols of Gold and Silver: that there may be univerſal love and freedome, and warr ſhall ceaſe.</p>
            <p>Well, afterwards I had much joy within my ſelf, ſo much that I am not able to expreſſe, and which cauſed me to breake forth in ſinging and dancing; and afterwards <hi>I</hi> was taken in a ſhaking fit, and after the fit was over, <hi>I</hi> was forced to give my money to them that were with me, and did give them all that I had.</p>
            <p>So by the appearing of me (ſaith the eternall God) ſhall all migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, great and rich men, throw and diſperſe their ſilver and gold to them that have need, that <hi>there may be no complaining in our ſtreetes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after this, I beheld a company of men and women with Crownes of gold upon their heads; and I asked my God, what meaneth theſe to have Crownes upon their heads? and my God ſaid, theſe Crownes betoken victory, for theſe are they that have overcome all things by my power, and have come out of great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and now have <hi>I</hi> wiped from their eyes, all ſorrow and weeping, and they ſhall reigne with me.</p>
            <p>On the next morning about ſix a clock, as I was in my bed, I ſaw the ſame viſion as I did before, as ſoone as I ſaw the Army routed, and the General ſlaine, I cryed out, they are now cut downe; and ſo I did at the night before twice or thrice, <hi>I</hi> cryed they are cut downe, and did afterwards expreſſe a bundance of joy, both as it appeared by ſinging and lifting up of my hands; and in this fit, I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165764:11"/> was commanded to declare it to the General, and was told me by a voice within me, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould have no reſt until I had declared it. And I asked who it was that commanded me to declare it? and the voice ſaid, <hi>I am that</hi> I <hi>am, the Lord of hoſſs, the King of Iſrael,</hi> and thou maiſt know <hi>I</hi> have made choice of thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale theſe things, and that I have commanded thee to declare it to the General, and that my purpoſe is now to deſtroy all powers; yea, the Parliament, and that this viſion is from God: thou ſhalt be preſently taken in a ſhaking fit, and in a very little while <hi>I</hi> was taken ſo; and <hi>I</hi> deſired my brother that lay with me, to lie upon me, and ſo he did, to try whether I ſhould then ſhake, and <hi>I</hi> did tater him up and down and ſhake ſo much, that he could not make me lie: &amp; about two a clock at noone, and on the morrow morning, I heard the ſame words as <hi>I</hi> did relate; that <hi>I</hi> have made choice of thee to reveale theſe things, &amp; that thou maiſt know that <hi>I</hi> have commanded thee to declare theſe to the Generall, and that this viſion is from the Lord of hoſts, and that thou ſhalt have no reſt untill thou haſt done it; thou ſhalt be taken in ſuch a ſhaking fit, as thou ſhalt be ſhaken more then ever thou haſt been yet, and ſo <hi>I</hi> was of a ſudden: thus perceiving <hi>I</hi> ſhould be ſhaken, I laid me upon a bed, and called a man that was in the roome to lie upon me, and ſo he did lie upon me, and <hi>I</hi> ſhook him as if he had beene in a Cradle, and rocked by a man: And I deſired to know what <hi>I</hi> ſhould declare to the Generall, and my God told me, I ſhould declare that it was his determination to bring to nothing the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and ſo deſtroy all powers beſides himſelfe, that he may be <hi>all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the fourth day of the ſecond of <hi>February</hi> in the morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween five or ſix of the clock, at the appearing of my eternall God to me; and indeed I had great cauſe for to rejoyce: for my father within me, told me ſaying, <hi>I</hi> thy comforter, thy Redeemer &amp; Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our wil declare ſome things unto thee: &amp; after my fleſh left trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: I heard a voice ſaying, behold, behold, what doſt thou now ſee? and I beheld, and loe there appeared a company of men, and <hi>I</hi> told them and there were ſeven, that were very gallant, ſome of them had Sattin cloaths, and ſome of them were in cloaths that were laced with Gold and ſilver lace: and they had each of them two or three men a piece waiting on them, and they were merry: and I ſaid, Lord, what meaneth theſe? &amp; the Lord anſwered me, &amp;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165764:11"/> told me; That theſe doth repreſent the Parliament; and as the were very merry amongſt themſelves, <hi>I</hi> beheld &amp; there appears a hand upon the wall and writ theſe words, <hi>Mene, Mene, Tek: Peres:</hi> and <hi>I</hi> asked the meaning of this writing: and <hi>I</hi> was told that they were weighed in a ballande &amp; were found too light: &amp; their Kingdom ſhall be taken from them and given to others: &amp; I beheld them that they were very ſad and hung down their heads at the appearing of this writing: and I heard a voice ſay, crie, crie, and <hi>I</hi> ſaid, what ſhall I crie? crie that the Lord of hoſt will bring down the Power, ſtrength and might of men, and will lay their honour ie the duſt: for my determination is to powere out upon them the fierceneſſe of my wrath and indignation, and all the earth ſhall be devoured with the fire of my jealouſie: <hi>for the day of the Lord is come that burneth as an oven and all they that do wickedly ſhal be as aſhes under the ſools of my feet; &amp; I will take the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to my ſelfe and give it to my Saints:</hi> and after this was over: within a very little while my eternall God within me, uttered theſe words again: behold, behold, what doſt thou now ſee? &amp; loe I beheld a company of men &amp; women Singing and dancing together with Crowns of gold upon their heads: and I looked on them, and did ſee them put their hands in their pockets, and they pulled out their money and gave it to one another: &amp; preſently after this I ſaw a company of men which were verry gallant (with their men waiting upon them) come to them and bowed to them: And I ſaid, Lord what are theſe that dance and ſing together? and the Lord ſaid, that theſe are my Sons and daughters, and three crownes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token victory: that they have through the ſtrength of me over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſinne and fleſh, and now are come to Sion with everlaſting joy and rejoyceing, and ſorrow and ſighing is fled away; and theſe ſhall reigne with me. And whereas thou ſeeſt Lords &amp; Knights &amp; their men come with bags of Gold &amp; ſilver, bowing &amp; preſenting their money to them that were danceing: theſe ſhew the fullfilling of Scriptures: <q rend="inline">"that the ſons of them that afflicted thee ſhall come bending down to the ſoles of thy feet &amp; ſhall call thee the bleſſed of the Lord, the Sion, the holy one of Iſrael, &amp; that the Kings, and the fulnes of the Gentiles ſhall bring their glory and honour to it:</q> and as thou ſeeſt my ſonnes receive their treaſure, and upon the reciving of it they became one, and their men put on their Hats, and were no longer SERVANTS but Fellowes with them: the time is now at hand that J will be ſuch a terror to all men that they ſhall throw away their idols of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165764:12"/> one to the other, for feare of the Lord, and for the glory of my Majeſtie, when I ariſe to ſhake terribly the earth: that they will no longer aſſume unto themſelves, ſuch a Preheminence as formerly they have done.</p>
            <p>And after a little while <hi>I</hi> heard theſe words utter'd within me againe: behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo I beheld an Angell with a ſickle in his hand come into a field of wheat; and I heard a voice ſay, thruſt in thy ſickle, for the harveſt is ripe: and I ſaid, Lord, who is this that hath a ſickle in his hand? and the Lord ſaid, this is my meſſenger that I have ſent; and the ſick'le in his hand is my power; by which he ſhall reap the harveſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, And lo <hi>I</hi> ſaw him thruſt in his ſickle, and cut downe all thoſe that were higher then the reſt, and ſo made all equall; and all the field became as one, in greatneſs none bigger then another. And <hi>I</hi> ſaid, Lord, what doth this field repreſent? and the Lord told me, That the field of wheat are men, and as you ſee the great eares cut from the little ones until they were all alike; ſo will <hi>I</hi> by my own power and by my bright appearing in my ſons and daughters; <hi>Cut down the loftineſs of men, and bring low their haughty lookes:</hi> and I like a mighty Leveller, <hi>will lay low-the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains &amp; hills, and make them as a plaine; and will make crooked pathes ſtraight, that I alone may be exalted:</hi> and ſo will take away that ſtumbling-block of private intreſt, that men ſhall no longer ſeeke for honour, as to warr one with another: but <hi>I</hi> will make them <hi>beat their ſwords and ſpeares into plowſhares preuning &amp; hookes,</hi> that there may be univerſall peace and freedome, and all dwell in love together.</p>
            <p>But in a little while after this, <hi>I</hi> heard the ſame words within me uttered. Behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo <hi>I</hi> beheld a mighty Angel going from one end of heaven to the other, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen, and is thrown into the Sea, that it ſhall never riſe more.</hi> And my excellent Majeſtie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me (which is my eternal God) ſaid, by Babylon is meant all forms of governments and ways of worſhips which men have ſet up, and all Lawes which men have made to keep their fellow-crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in bondage and ſlavery: but as thou ſeeſt this Angel throw a ſtone into the ſea and the ſtone never riſe more: ſo will <hi>I</hi> by mine own power take away the power of man for ever making any more Laws (to hang men) e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e long, and ſo will deſtroy the ſearlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collour'd whore, and will ſlit her noſe and <hi>burne her fleſh with fire;</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:165764:12"/> for the heaven and the earth ſhall now flie away and there ſhall be no more place found for it.</p>
            <p>And after this J heard the ſame words utter'd within me again. Behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo <hi>I</hi> beheld a mighty Angel crying aloud, <hi>the Kingdomes of this world are now become the Kingdoms of God, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever: and now the myſtery of God which hath bin hid ſhall be made manifeſt; and time ſhall be no longer; and now are former things paſſed away, and all things become new.</hi> And J ſaid, Lord, what is meant by this Angel? and the infinite God <hi>(by whom we live and move and have our being)</hi> ſaid that this Angel holds forth my ſervants crying againſt the powers of this world, and crying me up as the onely power that they will ſet up: and as he cried the myſterie of God <hi>is now finiſhed and time ſhall be no longer,</hi> it ſhewes that my ſons and daughters ſhall ſee &amp; know the myſterie of God; which myſterie is, God in them: and that they ſhall now ſay, <hi>time ſhall be no longer:</hi> by Gods working ſo powerfully in them burning up ſin and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, that ſo ſin and fleſh or Satan, ſhall no longer have any power over them; but God <hi>will be their all and in all,</hi> &amp; they ſhal now ſe it and know it too; which will occaſion them to crie <hi>time ſhall be no longer.</hi> And thus by the ſtrength of me (who am the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>omega)</hi> they overcome all things, &amp; ſo <hi>all things are become new:</hi> &amp; ſo my ſons &amp; daughters ſhall inherit all things: for the Angel after he had cried <hi>all things are become new:</hi> ſo he cried, they ſhall inherit all things: for my ſons and daughters (ſaith my God) ſhall now ſee me to <hi>be all and in all,</hi> and ſo ſhall ſee and inherit all things by the injoyment of me: for the myſterie being finiſhed in you, <hi>and all things become new:</hi> it is ſuch a change in you, that thoſe things that you thought were unlawfull before, will now appear to be lawfull: for this is the new thing, you will now ſee and know that all things are Gods, and ſo will ſee and know that as God is yours, ſo all riches, as houſes or Lands, are as much yours as any mans; for ſaith God; <hi>time ſhall be no longer.</hi> You ſhall know this (ſaith God) that ſinne and tranſgreſſion being finiſhed with you, and everlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe brought into you, and ſo ſwallowed up with righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, living in God, and God in you, you ſhall know <hi>that my worke, my ſtrange work which</hi> I <hi>wil do,</hi> is now to break in pieces al things, and to make all things become new: which change is to reſtore the whole creation from bondage and ſlaverie, <hi>into the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the ſons of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d;</hi> and ſo to take off the curſe that is upon all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165764:13"/> crearures, and to reſtore the creation to the firſt eſtate, as <hi>Adam</hi> was ſet in; that as <hi>I</hi> made <hi>Adam</hi> Lord over all creatures, and all creatures were for the uſe of <hi>Adam</hi> (ſaith the Lord) ſo now ſhall all the creatures men and women, have that priviledge (which by reaſon of the curſe) have a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng time bin deprived of as to have the injoyment of the outward creatures, which now they ſhall have: for as the appearing of me in one ſingle perſon Jeſus Chriſt my anoyted Son, did cauſe a communion to be among my Saints in thoſe dayes; ſo at the appearing of me in my ſons and daughters now, I will cauſe union and fellowſhip to increaſe, firſt amongſt my ſons and daughters, and then will burne up ſome by my ſpirit in them, and will confound others by might and power; and will make ſuch a ſtrange worke, that <hi>I</hi> will make all ſorts and degrees (ſome for feare of me, and ſome from the injoyment of me) give up give up, and relieve one another; that there may be univerſal love, peace and freedome; all enjoying the worke of my hands without let or hindrance,</p>
            <p>And being carried above my ſelf (or taken out of my ſelf) with joy, I burſt forth crying <hi>Halelujah, Halelujah, the Lord omnipotent reignes:</hi> but could not reſt my ſelf contented until I did burſt forth with ſinging, becauſe of the abundance of joy I was in.</p>
            <p>And on the 5. day of the ſecond moneth in the morning, came the word of the Lord unto me and ſaid,, I come: which made my fleſh to tremble: and at length I heard theſe words within me, behold <hi>I</hi> come to reveale unto thee things that muſt ſhortly come to paſſe: therefore behold what thou now ſeeſt. And lo, I beheld a great water, for the bigneſſe of it I could ſee no earth or ground; and in the midſt of it a woman gloriouſly araied, ſitting on a throne with a Crowne upon her head, and preſently there came one with a ſword in his hand, and cut off her head, and ſhe and her head tumbled into the ſea: and I ſaid (Lord) what meaneth theſe waters and this woman that ſitteth thereon? And the man that came with a ſword in his hand and cut off her head; and my eternall God (within me) ſaid: that the waters and multitudes of people: and the woman, is the Queen or the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> mentioned in the Revelations, <hi>that hath made all nations drunk with her forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and this Queen, or lady, that ſaith ſhe ſhould ſee no ſorrow: is Governments, and worſhips, and lawes which men have made and ſet up; and the man that came with a ſword in his hand and cut off her head; is my meſſenger which J have ſent, or my ſelf
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165764:13"/> appearing in my ſons and daughtera, which will cut off all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as Kingly and Parliament powers, and ſo will deſtroy all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments and forms of worſhips. And when her head was cut off: I heard a lamentation, men and women weeping and grieving, and ſome I ſaw were laughing and ſinging, crying <hi>Halelujab, Halelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah; for thou art worthie to receive Glory, and Honour, and praiſe; for thou haſt Judged the great whore, and taken vengeance on her for ſhedding the blood of the Saintt.</hi> And I ſaid (Lord) who are theſe that weep? And who are theſe that rejoyce? and the Lord ſaid that theſe are the Prieſts and thoſe that have bin made rich by her fornications that weep and howle: as the Prieſts that have made merchandiſe of ſouls of men: but now their trade is deſtroyed, and they ſhall no longer preach as to receive money for it; therefore they weep: but theſe are my ſons that ſing and rejoyce; and indeed they have now great cauſe for to ſing and rejoyce, becauſe that which hath troubled them (as formes and worſhips) are now deſtroyed: and I ſaid Lord, wilt thou deſtroy the Parliament? and the Lord ſaid, I will begin firſt in this nation, and will by my bright appearing burn up ſome, and deſtroy others: that there ſhall (to mens apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) be nothing but confuſion; for I will make great and mighty men run into the holes of the rocks, and throw away <hi>their Idols of gold and ſilver</hi> for fear of me, that there may be univerſal love and freedome. And I will be ſuch a terror to the great men, they ſhall hide themſelves for fear of me. And I ſaid (Lord) wilt thou do this by thy own power without making uſe of any Inſtruments? and the Lord ſaid no: but I will harden the hearts of the Parliament, and they ſhall raiſe an armie for to fight with the Generall, whom <hi>I</hi> will ſtir up to oppoſe their crueltie, and their actions, and ſo will deſtroy their power by my Inſtruments: and I ſaid Lord, ſhall <hi>I</hi> go and declare this to the Generall as yet or no? and the Lord ſaid wait upon me as yet and thou ſhalt know more, for <hi>I</hi> have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things elſe to reveal unto thee.</p>
            <p>And at night about eight of the clock on the ſame day, being in my chamber, the word of the Lord came unto me ſaying, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, behold, what doſt thou now ſee? And <hi>I</hi> looked and loe a white horſe and one upon him with a ſword in his hand ready drawn: and he rid from Eaſt to Weſt, and from North to South, cutting down all men and women, that he met with, that were higher then the middle ſort, and raiſed up thoſe that were lower then the middle ſort, and made them all Equall, and cryed out epquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165764:14"/> equalitie, in that <hi>I</hi> have now made all men alike: and he lifted up his hands to heaven, and did ſweare <hi>by him that liveth for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, time ſhould be no longer;</hi> and ſo did thruſt his ſword into his ſcabberd again. And I ſaid, Lord, who is this that makes all alike? and my glorious God within me ſaid: that I the Lord of hoſts have done this: and I ſaid, without any inſtruments Lord? and the Lord ſaid, no: but by inſtruments which I have choſen to do this ſtrange work: which ſhall cut down all powers, even the Parliament, and <hi>I</hi> ſaid Lord, ſhall the Parliament raiſe forces againſt thy inſtruments to fight with them? and the Lord ſaid they ſhall, but they ſhall be deſtroyed by <hi>Fair.</hi> (whom <hi>I</hi> have made choice of, and his Army: and whereas he cryed, <hi>time ſhall be no longer,</hi> and ſo put up his ſword into his ſheath againe: the meaning is: that when the time appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is come, all viſible powers ſhall ceaſe: and <hi>I</hi> alone <hi>will be all and in all,</hi> both King and Parliament, and Governor; and then wars ſhall ceaſe. And as you ſee him make all alike; ſo will I deſtroy ſome, and burne and conſume others, and be as a terror to the reſt; that there ſhall be none greater or richer then others. And I ſaid, how long will it be firſt? and the Lord ſaid, in a very little while it ſhall come to paſſe, but wait thou upon me and thou ſhalt know; upon this <hi>I</hi> deſired of my God, that if he had judged me worthy to reveale this viſion to me, and that it ſhall come to paſſe, and that it was from the Lord of hoſts: <hi>I</hi> might have ſome token that <hi>I</hi> may know it to be from God: and my God ſaid within me. That <hi>I</hi> ſhould be preſently ſhooke as if <hi>I</hi> ſhould be ſhoock to pieces, as a token that he had made choice of me to reveale this viſion and the reſt to, and that it ſhould ſurely come to paſſe: which token proved true, for <hi>I</hi> was preſently ſhoaken, even ſo much that two men (which were in the roome with me, that <hi>I</hi> deſired to lie upon me or hold me from ſhaking, which they did) could not keep me from ſhaking.</p>
            <p>But before this fit came on me one houre and halfe or ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>I</hi> ſaw a company of men and women, ſinging and dancing, giving away their money one unto the other: and my God within me, told me, that theſe were my ſons and daughters that were come to <hi>Sion;</hi> and that he had now wiped all teares from their eyes: and that ſelf-ſeeking is now ended with them: and inſtead of it there ſhall be univerſal lvoe, or a communitie, like unto the communitie of his Saints mentioned in the Acts: whereupon I was forced for my owne reſt, to give away that little money <hi>I</hi> had,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165764:14"/> about me: which thing others ſhall be made to do hereafter.</p>
            <p>Againe the word of the Lord came unto me ſaying (about one a clock on the 6. day of <hi>February)</hi> Behold, behold, what doſt thou now ſee: and lo! I beheld an Army of men with their drums beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and their colours flying, and they were upon their march: And I beheld till there came one to their General, being all glorious: and gave the General a ſword, and ſaid take this ſword, for with it ſhalt thou beat down all thine enemies: and I ſaid Lord, what is this Generals name? and the Lord ſaid his name is <hi>Fairfax;</hi> the Army that are with him are my inſtruments whom I have ſtirred up to hate the oppreſſion, covetouſneſſe and crueltie, of the Parliament. And whereas thou ſeeſt one give him aſword. It is I the Lord of hoſts, that have given him power to beat down all thoſe that are coming to fight wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h him: and preſently I beheld another Army of men coming to fight with them: and I ſaid, Lord, who doth this Army fight for? and the Lord of hoſts ſaid, they fight for the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: and the Lord ſaid, I ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red him up to oppoſe the Parliament, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cauſe they have exerciſed crueltie upon my people: and <hi>I</hi> beheld ſo long, that at length <hi>I</hi> did ſee both theſe meet together and did fight; and <hi>I</hi> beheld ſome now and then dropped down of <hi>Fair.</hi> his men; but they fell apace on the other ſide: but at length <hi>Fair.</hi> horſe routed the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her horſe, and followed ſome of them in purſuit; and ſome of them came and fell upon the foot, and at length broke in amongſt them and routed them, and tooke the General and killed him, and ſo had the field.</p>
            <p>And <hi>I</hi> ſaid Lord, wilt thou alſo deſtroy the Parliament? and the Lord ſaid he would do it. for ſaith the Lord, <hi>I</hi> will now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urne <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller,</hi> and will level mountaines and hills, and will make them equall with low places and vallies; that there may be univerſality. And <hi>I</hi> ſaid, how long will it be firſt? and the Lord ſaid in a very little while and it ſhall come to paſſe, and I ſaid, Lord, ſhall <hi>I</hi> go to the Generall and tell him of it? and the Lord ſaid <hi>I</hi> ſhould go: but ſhould ſtay a little longer firſt. And ſaith the Lord, whereas <hi>I</hi> ſaid (when <hi>I</hi> ſhewed thee this viſion at the firſt) <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt have no reſt untill thou hadſt done it:</hi> ſo <hi>I</hi> have troubled thee ever ſince day by day, and will till thou haſt done it: but thou ſhalt ſtay a little longer and wait upon me; and that thou maiſt know, I <hi>the Lord of Hoſts the mighty God of Jacob, by whom thou liveſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oveſt, &amp; haſt thy</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:165764:15"/> 
               <hi>being hath done this,</hi> Thou ſhalt be preſently taken in a ſhaking fit: that thou maiſt know I have made choice of thee: which fit of ſhaking came on me as ſoone as the words were ended: which terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied my fleſh, but my Spirit rejoyced within me for joy.</p>
            <p>And in a little while after: the Lord within me ſaid; behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo, I ſaw <hi>the heavens roleld up together as a Scroul:</hi> and figges fall off the figg-tree before they were ripe: and I ſaid Lord, what is meant by the heavens rolling thus together as a ſcroule? and the Lord ſaid, by the heavens, is meant, all outward adminiſtrations or forms of worſhip; preaching and baptizing: and I ſaw one throw the ſrcoule into the fire, and it was conſumed; ſo ſaith the Lord, ſhall all outward heavens be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up; and the figg tree is the Parliament in this nation, and it repreſents all powers which are a bringing forth ſome young figgs, which are ſome new formes or wayes of worſhip, or a doing ſome new thing, but before they can bring them to perfection, the day of the Lord overtakes them, and ſhakes them, and cauſes the figgs to fall off before they be ripe: and ſo I the Lord deſtroy the things that men would do.</p>
            <p>And the Lord again ſaid: behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo, I beheld foure men ſtand upon the foure corners of the earth; which is Eaſt, Weſt, North and South, and they held the winde in their hands that it could no longer blow upon the earth or Sea: and I ſaid Lord, what meaneth theſe foure men to do thus as they do? and my excellent Majeſtie the Lord of hoſts ſaid, theſe foure men are my ſons and daughters in whom I have ſpread my ſelfe through out the world. And by the wind which they hold in their hands, that it ſhould blow no more upon the earth or Sea: is meant all outward formes or wayes of worſhip, which of one kind or other have bin in all places, ſet up by men: but now I have taken their power from them, and have given it to the Saints; and by my bright appearing in them, they ſhall not ſuffer any formes or wayes of worſhip to be ſet up.</p>
            <p>And again the Lord ſaid: behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and I beheld a <hi>Throne and one that ſet thereon; before whoſe face hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth fled away, and there was no place</hi> for them: and <hi>I</hi> ſaid what is meant by this Throne? and the Lord ſaid, by this Throne is meant my ſons and daughters: and as you ſaw one that ſat thereon: tis I the Lord of hoſts who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> rule and reigne in my ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and they are my temple and houſe wherein I dwell: and by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165764:15"/> the heaven and earth that fled away is meant: all earthly powers, Governments and formes and wayes of worſhip, all outward admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, which by the appearing of me the God of Gods, ſhall be conſumed and burned up; that they may never be more: but that I the God of Gods, may appear to be their teacher and ordinances, and ſo <hi>all and in all:</hi> and ſo my Covenant of grace ſpoken off by <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> my ſon, be fulfilled: you <hi>ſhall not need to ſay, know the Lord: ſo they ſhall know me from the leaſt to the greateſt:</hi> and that other Propheſie, <hi>ye ſhall be taught of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And on the ſeventh day of <hi>February,</hi> The word of the Lord came unto me, and ſaid behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou? and loe, I beheld, and there appeared a table and a cloth laid upon it, and trenchers and napkins upon it, and ſtooles pulled out for men to fit upon them: and one cried with a loud voyce, come all ye fowls of the heavens to the ſupper of the great God: and preſently there were diſhes of all ſorts of meat ſet upon the table: and after this I ſaw three froggs creeping up and down, and at length they entred into Kings and Lords, and great men; and preſently they gathered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together and their armies; and I ſaid Lord, what is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Table; and of the things that are there on? and my God ſaid, the table is the earth: and the things thereon being of all ſorts, repreſent, all things in the earth: and I ſaid, what is he that makes the ſupper? and calls all the foules of the heaven to come to it? and my eternall God within me ſaid: it is I the Lord of hoſts that make this ſupper, and invite the foules to it: and I ſaid, what foules? and the Lord ſaid: by foules you muſt underſtand; my ſons and daughters who live in the heavenly injoyment of me: and they have all ſorts of things here to ſupper: <hi>I,</hi> even the fleſh of Kings, and Lords, and <hi>mighty men,</hi> and captaines, and of all both <hi>ſmall and great, bond and free:</hi> it ſhewes that the day is now a coming that they ſhall have the full injoyment of all creatures, and ſo ſhall inherit all things: the fleſh of Kings and great men which they eat, is the wayes of worſhips and formes of governments which they have ſet up: their eating of them, ſhewes a final conſumation of them, as that they ſhall be conſumed and never be more: the three froggs that went into the King and great men of the earth; are the ſpirits of devills, which is the proud fleſh domineering over the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, &amp; ſo ruling in their hearts, maks them raiſe armies of men, &amp; gather their forces together to reſiſt the appearing or coming of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:165764:16"/> me ſaith the Lord of hoſts: And thus through the pride of their hearts and loftineſſe of their ſpirits, they gather <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> together, to compaſſe the Saints round: But <hi>I</hi> ſaid, what is meant by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog?</hi> and the Lord ſaid, by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> is meant, all the wiſdome, power, and ſtrength of proud fleſh, which the great and wiſe men of the earth have invented, as their power on one ſide, and their falſe wayes of worſhips, and formes of governments on the other ſide, and Lawes which they have made, to make the Saints and people ſubmit unto, are the great armies that compaſſe the Saints round, or make war with me, ſaith God: But you ſee fire come out of heaven and burne them up; ſo by the bright appearing of me, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, ſhall all the enemies of my Saints (which have deceived them) be conſumed and burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d up; as formes, and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and wayes of worſhips, that they may be no longer deceived by them: and I beheld the Devil that had deceived them; and I did at length ſee him thrown into the lake of fire that burneth with brimſtone, <hi>there to be tormented with the falſe Prophet</hi> day and night: and I ſaid, what is meant by the Devil thrown into the fire? and my God ſaid, by the Devil is meant all the wiſdome, cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and craftineſſe of proud fleſh, which hath invented formes, and wayes of worſhips to deceive the people: they are all now burnt up and conſumed by the fire of my jealouſie, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, and are to be day and night tormented by me: That is, all proud fleſh and falſe Prophets (which is the wiſdome of the fleſh) ſhall from day to day, and from night to night, be under my wrath, and afraid to looke me in the face: and ſo by my appearing (ſaith <hi>the Lord of hoſts, who am a conſuming fire)</hi> ſhall they be tormented: who? all fleſh and filthineſſe, the power and wiſdome of men <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog:</hi> that I (the Lord of hoſts) may be <hi>all in all:</hi> For this lake of fire, is my w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath (ſaith God) into which I have judged and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced proud fleſh (that oppoſes me and throwne it; that ſo I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume proud fleſh, and bring it to nothing.</p>
            <p>And againe the Word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, what ſeeſt thou now? and I looked, and preſently I ſaw a great City, which to me did appear to be very gallant, as if there were none like it: and I ſaid, Lord, what meaneth this City, or what Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is this? and my Eternall God within me ſaid, this great City is ſpirituall <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where the Son of God was crucified: and I ſaid, Chriſt was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> though he was (ſaith
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:165764:16"/> the Lord of hoſts) put to death by the <hi>Jewes,</hi> yet he was alſo crucifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> that is, the Lawes, and formes, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> is <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> becauſe their Lawes and formes did ſlay my Son; and though he was put to death literally a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yet he was perpetually ſlaine by the filthy abominations of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> as Rebellion and diſobedience againſt me the Lord of hoſts: and ſo (ſaith the Lord of hoſts) all formes, Lawes, governments, and wayes of worſhip oppoſing me, is ſpiritual <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> that put to death my Son Chriſt, and hath from time to time, been the great whore that hath ſhed the blood of my Saints. But as thou ſaweſt one ſet it one fire, and the people which thou ſaweſt running to quench it, as Kings, and Lords, and great men, and of all ſorts of men, with buckets of water, and hookes, to pull down ſome of it, that was on fire, but they could not quench it, as thou didſt ſee untill the tenth part of it was conſumed: I the Lord of hoſts (by my appearing in my ſons and daughters) have ſet this City on fire, and it hath been burned a long time; by my manifeſting my ſelf to them to be their <hi>all in all:</hi> and now the day of my judgement is at hand; I have ſentenced this City to be burnt, for I the Lord of hoſts, doe burne up and conſume all formes and governments of men by my ſelf, <hi>I being a conſuming fire:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, what meaneth that, that the tenth part of it and not all, is conſumed? and the Lord ſaid, by the tenth part is meant all: for ten is a perfect number; as <hi>ten hornes</hi> mentioned, that ſets forth a perfect ſtrength, or all their ſtrength, or all their power: and I ſaid, Lord, it hath been generally underſtood, to be Nations, as our Nation for one, that ſhall fall off from <hi>Rome</hi> firſt, to be the City: but <hi>I</hi> the Lord of hoſts ſay, this City is formes and Lawes, Governments, and wayes of worſhip, which is in all Nations, and ſo is the <hi>ſpirituall Sodome and Egypt that crucified my Son;</hi> and hath from time to time, murdered my Saints: But the time of her power is almoſt at an end, and ſhe muſt be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>And whereas you ſee all ſorts of people run to quench the fire that it did not burne: It ſhewes the unwillingneſſe of all ſorts of men and women to have that which hath moſt deceived them, to be burned up; becauſe ſome, yea moſt, have made the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or traditions of men, to be their rule to walke by: and ſo have walked more by forme and cuſtorne then by any thing elſe: But now <hi>I</hi> come, <hi>I</hi> come, ſaith the Lord of hoſts; and I will take from <hi>men, &amp; from the powers of the world,</hi> thoſe things <hi>which they have gone</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:165764:17"/> 
               <hi>a whoring after:</hi> and they with all their might ſhall not hinder me from doing my worke.</p>
            <p>And the word of the Lord came againe unto me, ſaying, <hi>Behold, behold, what doſt thou now ſee?</hi> and lo, <hi>I beheld a Temple, and it was full of ſmoke;</hi> and there appeared one in this temple with a crown of gold upon his head; and his rayment was of all colours, like unto a rainbow: and <hi>I</hi> beheld that he ſtretched forth his hands; and as he ſtretched them forth, the ſmoke vaniſhed away: <hi>and I beheld that after the ſmoke was gon: there went out of his mouth flames of fire, and burned up the pictures that were in the Temple: and after they were conſumed he cryed with a loud voice that the fourtie and two moneths and the time, times and halfe times, is now come to an end and then the temple and holy city which for</hi> 42 <hi>moneths was given to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils to be troden under foot;</hi> ſhall now no longer be troden under foot: But <hi>I</hi> will redeem it and deliver it from the bondage and ſlavery that it hath bin ſubject unto: and after this <hi>I</hi> beheld ſeven lighted torch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es brought into the temple. And ſaid, <hi>I</hi> Lord whoſe temple is this? and the Lord ſaid, it is mine: and <hi>I</hi> ſaid, what doth this temple ſet forth? and the Lord ſaid; this temple are my ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: and he whom you ſee in it, is <hi>I the Lord of hoſts</hi> who am come to take poſſeſſion and to make them <hi>my dwelling-place:</hi> But as you ſee it was full of ſmoke: this ſmoke is darkneſſe, and gloomineſſe, and cloudineſſe, and ſuch a miſt, that untill it be conſumed, my people are not able to know me: but <hi>I</hi> ſaid, Lord it is ſaid, that no man was able to enter into the temple for the ſmoke: which ſeemes to hold forth the temple to be ſomewhat elſe then thy Saints: and the Lord ſaid; that is a metaphor which ſeems to hold forth ſome thing elſe, that is, my ſona and daughters are not able to come to the true knowledge of me, as to ſee and know that <hi>I</hi> live in them, without a more fuller diſcoverie of my ſelf to them, ſaith the Lord of hoſts: but as you ſee me ſpread forth my hands; and the ſmoke vaniſhed away, that they come to have ſome knowledge of me: but as you ſee flames of fire iſſued forth from me that burned up the pictures: theſe flames are a full manifeſting of my ſelf to my ſons and daughters: and the pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures, are all the wayes of worſhip, formes and governments which by the wit of man are ſet up: and as pictures reſemble ſomething elſe beſides what they are; ſo theſe formes, and wayes of worſhips, and governments, and all outward adminiſtrations, have ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared to be the way which I would have them obſerve:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:165764:17"/> Though indeed it hath been but a picture of me. Or my way: and not my right way, or mine own way, but a way of confuſion So that when I ſhall fully manifeſt my ſelf to my ſonnes and daughters: my ſpirit ſhall burn up all their pictures; that is, all their wayes of worſhip and formes of what ſort ſoever, <hi>and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them</hi> to nothing: <hi>for I the Lord of hoſts am a conſuming fire;</hi> and will ere long appear to be ſo: that they may ſee me to be forms and wayes of worſhips, and ſee me all and in all: and ſo to ſee that they ſhall have no need any longer of outward adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>But to ſee me to be their teacher: &amp; I ſaid, Lord what is meant by the temple or holy City that hath been troden under foot</hi> 42. <hi>months?</hi> by this temple or holy City; is meant, my ſons and daughters which for the time of Antichriſts reign hath bin kept in darkneſs, or in forms or wayes of worſhips which men have ſet up, and by his crying with a loud voice, he was come to deliver it from bondage or from the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and ſo from them both: it is I by my coming to Judge all the powers of proud fleſh which hath been an <hi>Alien and Gentile</hi> to me; and to deſtroy them, burn and conſume them up; as the forms of men and worſhips ſet up by them: that ſo I may deliver them from bondage, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, for the dayes of my coming is at hand.</p>
            <p>What doth theſe ſeven torches or lamps ſignifie? And the Lord ſaid: the ſeven lamps burning, ſhews a perfection of light that ſhall be. When the <hi>forty and two month</hi> (that are ſpoken of) <hi>ſhall be at an end:</hi> for theſe forty two months are a certain time, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, that I have ſuffered my ſelf to be hid: and my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hid from the Temple: but now the ſet time is at an end; and my light and glory ſhall ſhine: and as you ſee the lamps burning and none put them out: So will I appear burning up fleſh and ſin, and none ſhall hinder me from doing my work; ſaith the Lord of hoſts, that will reign in mount Sion for ever.</p>
            <p>And again the the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, what ſeeſt thou now? And I beheld, and ſaw the Moon, and the Sun, and the Heavens, and the Stars, and at length I ſaw them turned into bloud, and they fell from the place that they were in, and fell to the earth: and I ſaw a company of Swine and Dogs lick them up; they being like unto bloud, and with their falling upon the earth, the earth was changed: And I ſaid, Lord, what is this Sun, and Moon, and Heaven, and Stars, which is changed into blood? is it the material Sun that gives light by day, and the Moon that give light by night? And the Heaven; the Heaven that fouls fly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:165764:18"/> in? and my eternall God, within me, ſaid, No: but by theſe is meant other things: as the Moone is a borrowed Light from the Sunne, and not a perfect Light it ſelfe, ſo by the Moone is meant outward Ordinances that People have and are under, by which they have received ſome Glympſe of Light: but not the Light it ſelfe: by the Sun is meant a more glorious Diſpenſation of outward Ordinances, or Ordinances in a more higher Nature: As the one, being a Baptizing of Infants; and ſo they in this Diſpenſation, fetch Light from Creatures, or from the Men of this World, which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly have light, but have not: So the other which is of a more higher Nature: as the Baptizing of Believers, is a Sun-light (as they call it:) and ſo the Baptiſme-way of Baptizing Believers, and breaking of Bread together, is a way wherein, according to the Scriptures, they ſeeme to be more like the Sunne, than the other: but yet is not the way which I approve of, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: and the Heaven, is the Heaven of outward Diſpenſations, and Formes, and wayes of Worſhips, Governments, and Rules to walke by; that ſo long as People living under theſe, and do obſerve pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to fulfill theſe, as the obſerving the Sabbath Day, Praying, and Preaching, and going to Church, as they call it; and others meeting in private Places, as they thinke fit to meet in, and ſo to heare a Man ſpeake ſomething of God; this is Heaven which Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple live in, and meant by this Viſion, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: and the Starres is their profeſſions of God according to the ſeverall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations they are under: and ſo this Heaven, and the Starres therein, and the Sunne and Moone mentioned in Scriptures, turned into bloud, is meant, all outward Adminiſtrations, as Formes, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and Rules, and wayes of Worſhips, which have been as lights that People have ſeen ſomething of God in, and ſo have ſeen God at a diſtance from them, are now changed from light to bloud: and ſo are fallen from their places that they may no longer be as lights: and by the Dogges and Swine licking them up: is nothing elſe but a totall Diſtinction of them, that they may never be more: and the People <hi>may from hencefortb loath them: and ſee me the Lord of Hoſt, to be all, and in all, for my great and notable Day which theſe ſhall be turned into bloud:</hi> my coming to my ſonnes and daughters, and ſo judging all theſe things in them; and making of them dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; is the Earth that they fell upon: and was changed, and the Dogs and Swines (as is ſet forth by them a totall fall of Worſhips) by licking up the bloud: ſo by them is ſet forth the moſt greateſt and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:165764:18"/> moſt wickedſt Men: which have by their power ſet up theſe things, a change in them, that they ſhall no longer do ſo any more: but ſhall become new; for I have taken their power from them; and they are become new, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; and as thou ſeeſt a <hi>new Heaven,</hi> and <hi>a new</hi> Sunne and Moon in the place of the former, and a new earth; is but the fulfilling of Propheſies; that have a long tine ſince been ſpoken of; and now are come to paſſe; this new Heaven is the enjoyment of me; they living in me, and I in them; ſo they ſhall have no need of Heaven, of Ordinances or wayes to walk by; but I will be their light; both Sun and Moon; <hi>and ſo that they ſhall have no need of theſe lights to walk by: but I will be the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them: and as you ſee former things paſſed away and all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new, it is the paſſing away of the Sun, Moon, Stars, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> which are outward Adminiſtrations and Formes of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, Teachers of Men, that, I the Lord of Hoſt, <hi>may be both Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Sun, Moon, Stars, and Teacher to, and in them, that they may hear a voice, ſaying, this is the way, wallk in it:</hi> and the new earth is a change of Men, which have had power over their fellow Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and did deſire to have ſo, that they may be accounted great: but this was not an Earth wherein Righteouſneſſe dwelt: and ſo muſt paſs away; that there may be a new one; which new one is an alteration or change of Mens mindes; that as they have deſired a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, and have ſtrived to cozen and cheat others, for to make themſelves great, they ſhall no longer ſtrive for theſe; but <hi>inſtead of them, ſhall humble and abaſe</hi> themſelves, <hi>and throw away their Idols of Gold and Silver:</hi> their money, I mean, which they have made gods of, to them that have none, that there may be equality and <hi>univerſality,</hi> all injoying the fruit of the Earth, ſaith the Lord of Hoſt, who hath commanded the Writer hereof to write it, as my will and not his, that ſo <hi>all things may become now, and</hi> there may be an Earth <hi>wherein Righteouſneſſe ſhall dwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, the word of the moſt high, came unto me, ſaying, behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and low! I beheld ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt in the faſhion of an houſe; but it was not an houſe: and I ſaid, Lord, what is this? and my God ſaid, it is a taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle: and as you ſaw one with a Crown of gold goe into it: it was I the Lord that went into it: and I ſaid, is this the <hi>tabernacle of God, that is ſaid to be with men?</hi> and the Lord ſaid, it is: and this tabernacle is my people wherein I will dwell: and as he had a Crown of gold that went into it: it betokens a victory, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:165764:19"/> I have taken it to be my poſſeſſion: and as ſoon as I was in it, you ſaw flames of fire burn up the gold, pearles, and precious ſtones, and the wood hay and ſtubble; and preſently the Tabernacle that ſtood upon a foundation, had none: but hung onely by the power of him that went into it: <hi>this glold, pearles, precious ſtones, wood, hay, ſtuble, which was burnt up:</hi> are all manner of outward adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ever were, or is now at preſent; as formes, and lawes, and Governments, and rules of worſhips to walke by; which in one kinde or other have been highly eſteemed of all ſorts of men, according to the diſpenſation they have been under: and though they have laid Chriſt for a foundation, yet theſe hath been, in one ſort or other, the work which they have built upon: <hi>which work is to paſſe under</hi> the fire, for the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>every mans work ſhall be tryed by fire: and if any mans works ſuffer loſs, it will be by burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet he ſhall be ſaved ſo as by fire:</hi> which fire is my ſelf even I the Lord of hoſts) appearing in this tabernacle ſpoken of: which as ſoon as I did appear or entred in, all was conſumed, and burnt up: all the moſt glorious diſpenſations and formes of worſhips which in my abſence they have received comfort from: though all theſe outward adminiſtrations are conſumed, yet the creatures remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>ſaved by fire: that is, by my ſelf ſaith the Lord of hoſts, who am a conſuming fire:</hi> and as you ſee the temple as ſoon as theſe outward things? (gold, ſilver, wood, hay, ſtubble, were conſumed) It had no foundation: but was held up onely by the power of him that was in it between the heaven and the earth: ſo this is the ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate end of my burning up all the formes and waies of worſhips and rules of men, that they may ſee that they have not had me to be their foundation: for if they had, and had built right upon it: the droſſe would have been burnt from it, and they would have ſtood faſt, and not have been removed which now thou ſeeſt they are, and have no foundation: their worſhips and wayes being taken from them, they fall, if I by my own power, do not hold them mp: but I have to this end deſtroyed them all and routed them of their forces; that they may now ſtand by my power alone; and ſee me to be their lives, and their <hi>all and in all.</hi> &amp; that <hi>I would have them no longer receive</hi> comfort from ſtreams; <hi>but from me their fountain of life:</hi> &amp; as thou heards me ſay, I was <hi>a Alpha</hi> &amp; <hi>Omeg.</hi> &amp; they that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com <hi>ſhal inherit al things; &amp; I wil be their God, &amp; they ſhal be my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> if nothing elſe but a declaration that I am all and in all: and he that over comes muſt be by my power (who am the all of all things)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:165764:19"/> that he doth overcome ſome; fleſh, and Divell, and ſo by <hi>his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming he ſhall inherit all things;</hi> he ſhall inherit me, or enjoy me the Lord of hoſt; and I will in love communicate my ſelf unto him; and by injoying me, he ſhall injoy all things, for all the beaſts of the field, and all the houſes, and lands, and mony in the world is mine, ſaith the Lord of hoſt: ſo ſhall they be my ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and they ſhall have a full injoyment of them all: for as I made <hi>Adam</hi> Lord over all creatures, and made all creatures to be for the uſe of <hi>Adam;</hi> and <hi>Adam, ſo long as he ſtood, he did injoy them all: ſo will I now, ſaith the Lord of hoſis, recover my wool and my flax,</hi> and redeem the creation from bondage, and make ſuch a work in the earth, by my bright appearing, that the rich miſers ſhall howle and weep for depriving my ſons and daughters of the outward creatures; and their ruſty gold and ſilver ſhall ſo much riſe up in their conſciences, that they ſhall no longer ſayts theirs, but its the Lords; and ſo ſhall ſuffer my people, and all other poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that want the outward goods of this world, to have what they pleaſe, that there may be univerſal love, ſaith the Lord of hoſt.</p>
            <p>And the word of the Lord came againe unto me, ſaying, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo I beheld ſeaven men, and each of them had a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; and one of them ſeven ſounded his Trumpet, <hi>and the reſt did not; and as ſoon as he had done ſounding, there appeared one with a booke open in his hand, and lifted up his hands to heaven, and did ſwear by him that liveth for ever, time ſhould be no longer; but now the myſtry of God is finiſhed as he hath declared by the voice of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Apoſtles:</hi> And I ſaid, Lord, who be theſe Trumpeters? and my eternal God within me ſaid, theſe be my ſons which have from time to time ſounded an alarum to the world, &amp; as you ſee but one ſound, and the reſt did not: It ſhewes, that they that did not, had ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed already: That is, they according to their light, have preached and ſpoken againſt Antichriſt; and have given Antichriſt warning of what the ſeventh was to ſound; but now the ſeventh ſounds, the miſtery of God is finiſhed; that is, a great and glorious diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of light is now made manifeſt, more thenſever hath been, by the appearing of one, ſaith the Lord of hoſt; which makes my ſons and daughters know the miſtery which hath been hid, and ſo crie a loud that time ſhal be no longer: not onely crie, but through their knowledge, ſwear by God, <hi>that liveth for evermore, time ſhall be no longer:</hi> And I ſaid Lord, what is this miſtery that hath been hid
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:165764:20"/> and now is made manifeſt? and God ſaid, this myſtery, is my owne ſelfe making out of my ſelf to be <hi>all and in all:</hi> and that I doe not dwell in a place afar off, that is, onely Heaven, and onely there; but that my dwelling place is now in my Temples, which Temples are my ſons and danghters: and that I, who am the life and fulneſſe of all things, have been always the life of all creatures, and the life of man, and have been in man, but not knowne to bee there: but have beene covered under the clods of proud fleſh, but now the day of my appearing is come, that proud fleſh ſhall be deſtroyed; and all that have kept the creature from looking after me the Lord of Hoſt, within them: but have cauſed the creature to look after mee afar off: But now by my bright appearing, the book which thou ſeeſt in the Angels hands being open, will cauſe the myſtery to be known that I am in all men, and the life of all men: for this book is the myſtery, which myſtery is I the Lord of hoſt: and as the book is opened, ſo I the Lord of Hoſt, have made my ſelf, by my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judge proud fleſh, to be God in all men: manifeſting my ſelf in love to my ſons and daughters; <hi>and appear in wrath to mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> And I ſaid, Lord, <hi>what is meant that time ſhall be no longer,</hi> is it judgement? a diſſolation of the world? or that time ſhall be no longer to them that thou haſt manifeſted this myſtery to? <hi>or that time ſhall be no longer for the beaſt to reign? or the whore that hath ſhed the bloud of Saints?</hi> And the Lord ſaid, that by my appearing in my ſons and daughters, I will burn up ſin and fleſh, ſo that time ſhall be no longer with them; for they ſhall ſin no more, nor ſee no evil: <hi>which myſtery is a riddle to moſt men,</hi> that the Sains <hi>ſins &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions ſhould be finiſhed: but though it be a riddle and few know it, that the ſeventy weeks</hi> (for to make an end of ſin, &amp; to bring everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting righteouſneſs) <hi>is at hand;</hi> yet the ſounding of this Trumpet wil make more know it: I mean the Saints, I mean that the Saints ſhall ſee that they ſhall now no longer commit ſin; for <hi>tranſgreſſion is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and everlaſting righteouſneſs brought in,</hi> ſaith the Lord of hoſt: and by time that it ſhall be no longer, is meant, that ſet time which I the eternal God <hi>have allotted Antichriſt the man of</hi> ſin or the beaſt to reign, <hi>which was for forty and two months,</hi> but now the <hi>forty &amp; two months</hi> being expired, &amp; come to an end, all the powers of fleſh, Devil &amp; ſin, and that have been ſet up by the powers of this world, by Kings &amp; Lords, and great men, their power ſhall be taken from them, and ſo ſhal all time be at an end with them; I mean, their powers ſhall be deſtroyed, when the time is come as it is now, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:165764:20"/> the beaſt ſhall be deſtroyed: By the beaſt is meant, all forms and ways of worſhips, rules and Governments which is the wiſdome of the fleſh, as teaching and praying by the wiſdome of the fleſh, and living in outward adminiſtrations at a diſtance from God, and ſo thinking to make I the God of gods, in love with you for your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations and traditions: Time is come, <hi>and time ſhall be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> for theſe things, but all theſe I have judged <hi>to be burnt up as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Beaſt and fleſh of the Word: for the myſtey of God is now fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and time will ceaſe; that I the Lord of Hoſt may be all in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying: behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now: and lo I beheld a woman and ſhee was all in white, and not one ſpot to be ſeen about her: and ſhee had a Crown of gold upon her head, and in her right hand ſhee held a Scepter: and I did ſee men with Crowns of gold upon their heads, and other Gallants, and of all ſorts, come to her with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents: and ſome brought gold and ſilver, and ſome pearls, and ſome jewels, and ſome precious ſtones, and ſome one thing, and ſome another: and preſented them to her <hi>with bowing and bending.</hi> And one <hi>I did behold that proclaimed with a loud voice, that Jeruſalem was come down from heaven: and that the marriage of the Lamb is now come:</hi> and preſently I beheld one all in glory to come to this woman, who had a crown upon his head, and he went into the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and they became one, and the woman delivered her Crowne and Scepter to him that came to her, and preſently there cried out to make ſupper ready: and preſently I beheld a long table &amp; table cloth laid upon it, with trenchers and napkins, and ſtools pulled forth; and I beheld the diſhes brought to the table; and there was ſet on the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all manner of varieties that could be; and the gueſts were all in white: and there I ſaw them eat and drink, <hi>and were very merry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</hi> The time being come that <hi>all ſorrow and ſighing ſhall fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, what woman is this with a crown upon her head and a Scepter in her hand? and the Lord ſaid: this woman is the <hi>Jeruſalem that comes out of heaven, the Lambs wife:</hi> and as ſhe was all in white without ſpot: it was the righteouſneſs of I the God of gods; and her Crown and Scepter ſhews, that ſhe doth by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of me, overcome all her enemies, as ſin; fleſh and hell: and by the great men, as Kings and Lords, bringing preſents to her: it ſhews that <hi>I the Lord of hoſt hath ſet my houſe above all mountains: and that my people ſhall ſuck the riches of the Gentiles:</hi> and that thoſe, as Kings &amp; Lords, that have perſecuted her <hi>by the names of horeticks &amp;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:165764:21"/> 
               <hi>ſectaries, and have laughed at her, ſhall now come, bowing and ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the ſols of her feet; and ſhall a knowledge of a truth, that the God of gods is in them.</hi> And as thou ſeeſt one come to her, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into her, and ſhe gave him her Crown and Scepter: it ſhews that I the Lord of hoſts, and my people, ſhall no longer be two but one: and that I ſhall no longer appear to be in heaven a great way from them: but in them and one with them, married to them, their husband and joy: and as ſhe at his coming to her, delivered her Septer and Crown to him: it ſhews that by my manifeſting my ſelf in them, to dwell in them, and to be one with them: will make my ſons and daughters reſigne up all unto me: that ſo I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all their proud fleſh, and cover their nakedneſs with my righteouſneſs, ſaith the Lord of hoſts: and as you ſaw a table and all things thereon, as napkines and trenchers, and all manner of varieties, and the gueſts all in white: is nothing elſe but I my ſelf ſaith the Lord of hoſts: wherein is all manner of plentifulneſs; and that my ſons and daughters are here <hi>ſet forth to be the gueſts all in white: That is, waſhed and made clean by my righteouſneſs; are now come to the feaſt of fat-things, of marrow,</hi> and wine on the lees: where they my eat and drink and be ſatisfied with the fulnes of me. Therefore eate and drink, <hi>yea drink abundantly:</hi> and as they were at ſupper they were merry together, that is nothing elſe, but I injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and they enjoying me: I did fill them <hi>ſo full of joy as to make them merry, that I told them ſorow and ſighing ſhould now fly away:</hi> for my ſons and daughters that have been at this banquet and ſee themſelves married to me to be one with me: and ſo feed conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually <hi>of the bread of life,</hi> henceforth not knowing ſin, nor hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger any more, <hi>but being ſatisfied</hi> in living in the injoyment of me, <hi>ſaith the Lord of hoſts,</hi> who am life and joy, and time, as to ſin, ſhal be no longer: and ſo knowing no ſin: ſhall have no cauſe to ſee ſorrow, or to weep any more; for all thine enemies <hi>both within and without ſhall be deſtroyed: that thou mayeſt come with everlaſting joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing &amp; ſinging to Sion, ſaith the Lord of hoſts the holy one of Iſrael, who is in the midſt of thee, &amp; the days of thyweeping ſhall be at an end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me ſaying, behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? And loe! I beheld, <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> (mentioned in the <hi>Revelations)</hi> one more glorious then the reſt, and he had ſome thing in his hand, which I did not know, till I asked God: And then it was told me it was a vial: and he pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it forth upon great men, As Kings and Parliaments, and all ſorts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:165764:21"/> of men, and on the beaſt that comes out of the bottomleſſe pit, and on the Locuſt, and on the ſcarlet colloured whore that is decked <hi>with all manner of precious things: and they all became dead: and the remnant were affrighted and gave glory to God:</hi> and I ſaid Lord, what is the meaning that but one of them powred forth his vial? and the Lord ſaid, that the reſt had powred forth their vials &amp; had tormented the men of the earth already: but this one that powres forth his vial now, doth not onely torment but deſtroy the men of the earth: and I ſaid Lord, wilt thou take their lives from them that they ſhall be no longer? and my God, ſaid, I; I will take from them that which hath bin their life: but yet I will not take from all of them their natural life: but from Kings, and Parliaments &amp; great men; I will take from them their power, which they have had, and they ſhall inſtead of haveing power become humble and ſubmiſſive and be as lowly as the poor: for this vial is my wrath, that ſhal burne and conſume all fleſhly powers: and as he that powres it forth is more glorious then the reſt: it ſhewes my ſons &amp; daughters ſhall have <hi>more glorious diſcoveries</hi> and manifeſtations of me their <hi>God dweling in them,</hi> ſaith Lord of hoſt; and through <hi>the fulneſſe they have of me</hi> (I being in them) they <hi>ſhall now ſay, time ſhall be no longer:</hi> and I ſaid Lord what <hi>is the meaning of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit:</hi> and the Lord ſaid, by the bottomleſſe pit is meant the heart of man: and by the beaſt that riſeth out of it is not meant the Pope and Emperours: but is meant, all the wiſedome of the proud fleſh, that hath and doth ſtil invent all the wicked actions of men that have murdered the Saints: as formes and governments: and from this bottomleſſe pit ariſeth threatnings and malicious words, even ſuch there is hatcht within it as a man is never able to know from whence they come, or whether they go. For the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to death of Saints, is firſt contrived here in this pit; which I the Lord of hoſt doth ſay, is the heart of man: and then according as they have invented how and after what manner they ſhall put them to death, they put their power in <hi>execution to do it: and by the Locuſts, is meant the Prieſts; for as Locucts deſtroyes and devours the fruits of the earth,</hi> ſo have theſe Prieſts from time to time been the chief actors and ſetters on of the Kings and great men of the earth for to make Lawes for them to worſhip God by, as they call it; and ſo poor creatures have been deluded by them to worſhip ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but they nor the Prieſts knew not what, inſtead of me ſaith the Lord of hoſt; and ſo haue deſtroyed the earth, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:165764:22"/> bodies; and being Spiritual Merchants, <hi>they have not onely deſtroyed the bodies of men,</hi> but <hi>have alſo made Merchandize of the ſouls of nem;</hi> and all this they have done pretending they did preach to bring them to heaven: when indeed they rather did the things that was a cauſe of ignorance and darkneſs (by telling them they were the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God ſent to <hi>Preach, and that none was to preach but they, and</hi> ſo did keep them from the enjoyment of me, <hi>ſaith the Lord of hoſts)</hi> and to throw them into hell: ſo their preaching of me was more for their fat Benefices then to bring ſouls to me, as they made it appear to bee: for if at any time any did out-ſtrip them, or did doe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing tending to the ſetting forth the glory of me, or had ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of me, and ſo would teach for nothing; they muſt be heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and ſo muſt he cut off; and thus theſe prieſt-like Locuſt, have devoured men and kept <hi>them in bondage by their philoſophy and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing craftineſſe: but time ſhall be no more. And the woman which thou faw'ſt arayed with all manner of precious things, is the whore of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon: and her Scarlet Colloured cloathes and precious things,</hi> ſets forth her formes and wayes of worſhips, decked with outward zeale of profeſſions, ſo that they ſeem to the eye of men to be my way, ſaith the Lord of hoſt: for ſhe being ſo gloriouſly arayed, ſets forth all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adminiſtrations of what ſort ſoever: <hi>but time ſhall be no longer; for the vials of my wrath is now powered</hi> forth upon them all, and they ſhal all be conſumed and brought to nothing: and all theſe outward adminiſtrations, which ſeem'd before to have life; ſhal now be ſlaine and appeare to be dead: <hi>that I alone may be all and in all:</hi> ſuch is the worke that I wil now do <hi>that thoſe that ſhall be left alive ſhall be affrighted and give glory to me; for the remnant were affrighted and they gave glory to God:</hi> theſe of the earthly powers, as Kings and Lords, and of all ſorts of men that doth eſcape with their lives as they be not taken away, ſhal give glory to me: ſome of them <hi>by being purified and my ſons, and ſome of them by bringing their riches to my ſons and daughters:</hi> for thoſe that <hi>know not me I will be a terror to them and will make them throw away their Idols of Gold and Silver,</hi> and in ſo doing they ſhall glorifie mee: and I ſaid, are theſe that powred forth thy vials Angels that are inviſible, or be there no Angels but thy ſervants and ſons here below? and the Lord ſaid, that they that power forth my vials are my ſons, and my ſons are Angels, and miniſtring ſpirits: they are Angels: and the Angels mentioned in Scriptures, are no other but my ſons and daughters: and thoſe two Angels that came to <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> where two men:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:165764:22"/> but <hi>becauſe I made them my meſſengers, they were called Angels: and the Angel that ſmote the Aſſyrians and ſlew ſo many thouſands.</hi> Was a man whom I appointed to do that work, and ſo was called an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord, becauſe he did my will ſaith the Lord of hoſts: and for thoſe that think Angels are inviſible ſpirits, and ſo cannot be ſeen; and ſo doth likewiſe think, that I am in a place above the skies called heaven, and ſo think I have inviſible Angels to keep me company, are out of the way, and have miſſed of the miſtery; which I will now make manifeſt, ſaith the Lord of hoſt.</p>
            <p>The word of the Lord came unto me ſaying, behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? And loe, I beheld a woman cloathed with white, and black ſpots upon her Gown; and I beheld, and there came one with fire and laid it upon her cloathes, and the fire burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all her cloathes: and upon her breſt were knots of ſeveral ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons, but they were all conſumed: and ſo I ſaw her naked ſtript of all: but preſently he that burned her cloathes (and ſhe was not hurt in her body) brought her cloathes again to put on her all white without ſpot; and ſhe, to my thinking, was then far more glorious then ſhe was before: and I ſaid, Lord, what woman is this? And my eternal King ſaid: it was his Church: and as ſhe was in white it did ſhew that ſhe did apprehend her ſelf to be clean by Chriſt: as ſhe had black ſpots, it doth ſhew that ſhe is not ſo pure as to be free from imperfection: and as ſhe had knots of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ribons on her breaſt: it doth ſhew, that ſhe (the Church) hath ſeveral outward ordinances <hi>or diſpenſations,</hi> formes by which ſhe doth worſhip me, ſaith <hi>the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> but as you ſaw one came with fire and burnt all her <hi>cloathes and all her ribons; and yet did not hurt her body,</hi> it ſhews, that <hi>I the Lord of hoſt who am a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire,</hi> will burn all her droſs, or conſume all fleſhlineſs and droſs from my people, or Church; and ſo will ſtrip her naked of all her adminiſtrations, and outward ordinances, and Church-fellowſhips, and paſtors, and teachers, and of all though it ſeems never ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And as you ſaw he that burned up her cloaths, bring her new cloaths to put on all white without ſpot or wrinkle: it ſhews that I the Lord of hoſts: after I have burned up and conſumed all the fleſh and fleſhlineſs of my Church, as all her outward ordinances and diſpenſations, as formes of worſhips; and all her paſtors and teachers and Church-fellow-ſhips, and ſo they ſtriped her naked of all, that then I will new cloath her, that ſhe ſhall (the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:165764:23"/> Church) appear far more glorious then ever ſhe was before; for when ſhe is thus ſtriped of all and is naked in her own <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions; ſhe ſhall be cloathed with the Sunne mentioned</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations: <hi>and the Moon ſhall be under her feet:</hi> this Son is my righteouſneſs: which will make her (the Church) all in white: as you ſee the woman after ſhe had loſt all was cloathed in white, and all outward Ordinances (repreſented by the Moon) under her feet: that when my church is ſtripped of all outward excellencies, then ſhall I appear to be excellent: as to be her paſtor, and teacher, and ordinances, and ſo her <hi>all and in all,</hi> and then ſhall ſhe be more free and at more liberty, when theſe ſhall be taken from her, then ſhe hath been yet: for then my Church ſhall not run after men and ſo go gadding about for food: but ſhall quickly reſt her ſelf contented, with me the bread of life: <hi>and ſo ſhall worſhip me in ſpirit and in truth:</hi> and ſo my Church ſhall be <hi>compacted of living stones,</hi> that the propheſie <hi>may be fulfilled: there ſhall not be a Cananite in the houſe of the Lord any more:</hi> but ſhe ſhal now wholly throw away that which ſhee hath highly eſteemed of, as outward means: which hath been but ſtreams, which have flown from me <hi>who am the fulneſs of all things: and ſhall now wait onely to hear the voice within her ſaying, this is the way walk in it:</hi> and ſo heard this voice, which voice (is I the Lord of hoſts ſpeaking in her) ſhe ſhall have more ſatisfaction and reſt in her ſpirit then ever ſhe has had as yet: for ſhe thus wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon me; ſhall ſpeak the pure language, which none ſhall have but thoſe my ſons and daughters that I make out my ſelf unto: for the effect of this language (which is the ſpirit of me) will cauſe all difference and confuſion to end, that ſome ſhall no longer worſhip me the Lord of hoſts one way, and ſome another way: but being poſſeſt <hi>of me and hearing me</hi> teaching in them, I will make them all to <hi>ſerve me with one conſent,</hi> which cannot be, ſo long as they worſhip me in ſeveral forms: therefore do I this ſaith the Lord of hoſts, to ſtrip my people of all forms: that ſome might not run one way and ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; but that all may ſerve me in one way: which way is onely to wait on me, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, who wil bring it ſuddenly to paſs.</p>
            <p>And as thou ſaweſt one bring a book and it was ſealed: and he that brought it opened it and gave it her in her hand: this book is the <hi>miſtery of mee which is now to be finiſhed: and as you ſee it was ſealed up:</hi> it ſhews, that this miſtery (which is I the Lord of hoſts in my people) have been hid and none hath been able to look into it: but as he that opened it and gave it to her doth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:165764:23"/> ſhew, that though it hath been hid, yet (I the Lord of hoſts) will now open it and make it known to all my ſons and daughters; as the woman doth repreſent, by having it open in her hand, and when they ſhall ſee this miſtery, I the Lord of hoſts to be in them; then ſhall they know how to worſhip me, which will be without ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or forms, only waiting for me to teach them, and no longer to wait upon the teaching of man; for man hath teached them to look for me in heaven, or that I do dwell in heaven in a place above the skies, but they know not where, not teaching them to look for me within them, where they now, in waiting upon me, ſhall know that I do dwell ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, behold, behold, what doeſt thou now ſee? and loe, I beheld a beaſt that had upon his head one horn, and he continied puſhing until there came one and cut him down, and burned his body: and I ſaid, Lord, what beaſt is this? And my eternal Majeſty the King of eternal glory within me ſaid: this beaſt is that beaſt with one horn mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Daniel:</hi> and yet is the ſame beaſt mentioned in the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: That made an Image like unto the former beaſt: that had a wound and did live: which cauſed all both ſmall and great bond and free, to receive a mark in their foreheads or in their right hand, that they might live and have a being amongſt them: but here is wiſdom: let him that hath underſtanding count the number of the beaſt for it is the number of man: and his number is ſix hundred threeſcore and ſix:</hi> And I ſaid Lord what doth this Beaſt repreſent? That proceedeth from the Kings, and doth think to change laws and times: and had power given him until a time, and times, and dividing of times? And my eternal God within me ſaid: that this beaſt is, the Parliament: who have their poewr by reaſon the 10 horns are cut down: that is by reaſon Kingly power, as the name of it is cut off with the late King that was beheaded: and likewiſe theſe formes of worſhips as the Epiſcopal Government for matter of rules of worſhips to walk by; as to do as the Biſhops was pleaſed to have people do; they are all cut down by the Parliament: which the beaſt as thou ſaweſt did ſet forth: for as the beaſt that was to riſe after the Kings, ſhould be diverſe from the reſt: even ſo hath the Parliament been diverſe from King <hi>Charles;</hi> for though King <hi>Charles</hi> did oppreſs the people with ſhip money, which he ſhould not have done, and ſo did ſhew his cruelty and tyranny: yet the Parliament hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed as much cruelty upon the people as he did: for as <hi>Charles</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:165764:24"/> laid his little finger upon the people, the Parliament have laid their loynes: and for matter of oppreſſion to the people have been far more cruel then <hi>Charles</hi> that was before; and ſo have been <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</hi> from <hi>Charles:</hi> which word <hi>Divers</hi> ſhews more then one, though called by one: as the Parliament are more then one: yet being compacted together they are but one in reſpect that what is done, is done by conſent of all or moſt of them, and not by ſome few. And as the beaſt did think to change Times and Lawes, they being given into his hands: ſo the Parliament hath pretended to change times, that is, <hi>to take off the oppreſſion of people</hi> and Lawes; that is, to alter the Lawes of the Land: for the Parliament have had power to do ſo: and the Parliament have done theſe in ſome ſence; as the taking away the high Commiſſion Court and Star Chamber, inſtead of being Governed or having Biſhops; we muſt have claſſes and Presbyters, or at leaſt they have declared that <hi>we ſhould have: but though the firſt beaſt in the Revelations, had a wound with a ſword and did live;</hi> though high Commiſſion Court and Star Chamber, I mean the oppreſſion that was uſed by them, though the name be taken away; yet in regard of oppreſſion they live: for the Image of the beaſt, is nothing but the ſame oppreſſion: as to have a <hi>new name,</hi> as not to be the ſame: but by this <hi>new name,</hi> and ſo under this new name exerciſing cruelty and oppreſſion, is to make an Image, and ſo to repreſent the former: and though the Parliament have given themſelves a <hi>new name,</hi> by ſtiling themſelves a <hi>Free State,</hi> yet they are but the Image of the former beaſt: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard as the former exerciſed cruelty upon the people, and the Parliament doth the ſame: and as the beaſt mentioned in <hi>Daniel had power, and likewiſe in the Revelations, for to cauſe all both great and ſmall, to worſhip the Image of the beaſt that they might live.</hi> Even ſo the Parliament: by the ſetting forth their Engagement (as they call it) and by forcing all to take it (which was their intents when they ſet it forth) and ſo to deprive them of the benefit of the Law, for denying ſubmiſſion to this power or Image which they have ſet up, and ſo the mark which the Image of the beaſt hath ſet forth, and cauſed all to receive, doth repreſent the Parliament, who have ſet forth their mark, <hi>the Engagement</hi> (as they call it) for people to receive it, <hi>in their fore-heads;</hi> that is, to profeſs them to be the ſupreame power, <hi>and that they ought</hi> to worſhip them, and ſubmit to their Lawes: <hi>and on their right-hand,</hi> is meant, the aiding and aſſiſting of them with power and with money; that the former,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:165764:24"/> which was Kingly power, might not riſe again: but that they might be now adorned and have the honour: even the <hi>Parliament, ſeems to be the Image of the Beaſt, and the Engament the marke of the Beaſt but the Beaſt, or Image of other, is but for a time, times, and dividing of times, mentioned in Daniel,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Revelations, to be the forty and two moneths,</hi> which is a ſet time that this Image of the Beaſt ſhall have power; and when that ſet time is at an end, which I have appointed, this Beaſt ſhall be deſtroyed and burned to nothing; all their powers, and all their Laws and formes, and wayes of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and worſhips, and ſhall never riſe more, nor any like it, ſaith the Lord of hoſt: here is wiſdome! this wiſdome is I the Lord, and let him that hath underſtanding count the number of the Beaſt, and let him that hath my ſpirit and this wiſdom revealed from me to him count, for the number <hi>of the Beaſt: is the number of a man,</hi> the number of a man is his continuance, or abiding here in this earthly body before it returnes to the earth which number is ſet forth or appointed by me the Lord of hoſt, for his time here, before he be brought to the duſt of the earth; which number be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompliſhed and come to an end, man muſt come to the grave: ſo the Beaſt is numbered, his daies are ſet down how long he ſhall have Power, or how long he ſhall continue.</p>
            <p>By the Beaſt that is numbered here, is meant the Parliament or powers of the earth, which (I tel you) is the Beaſt that muſt be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or deſtroyed ſo ſoone as his time which I have let him, ſhall come to an end: for his number is ſix hundred threeſcore and ſix: which I the Lord of hoſt, tell you they are ſo many dayes that this beaſt ſhall have the whole power to himſelfe: that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall have for their time to raigne, from the day that they beheaded <hi>Charles</hi> ſix hundred and threeſcore and ſix dayes: and I ſaid, Lord, ſhall I take them to be litteral dayes, as fiveſcore to and hundred and ſo ſeven of them to make a week as we call it? and my God ſaid, you ſhall take them to be litteral dayes, and ſo count them from the day that <hi>Charles</hi> was beheaded: for that is and ſhall be the time of their power: and before theſe ſix hundred and ſixty and ſix come to an end, the Parliament ſhall be conſumed and deſtroyed and brought to nothing: and I the Lord of hoſt that hath revealed this viſion to thee, will ſurely bring it to paſſe; and that thou maiſt know that it is I the Lord of hoſt that have revealed this to thee, and that this is truth, I will preſently ſhake thee in a ſtrange manner more then ever I did at once, as a token
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:165764:25"/> to ſatisfie thee that theſe ſhall come to paſſe: and as ſoone as the voice which ſpake theſe words ceaſed, I fell a ſhaking, and was ſo ſhooke that I made the bed I lay in tatter, and was lifted up as if ſome body had tooke me up, and threw me down again, which one that lay with me can tell; for I told him before I ſhook, I had received words that I ſhould be ſhaken, which proved true, and I am ſatisfied in my ſelf, that that which I now write, will (to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Great men, and to the amaſement of all ſorts) prove very true, and that it is the pleaſure of the Lord of hoſt to bring to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing all earthly powers, that the Lord <hi>may be all and in all:</hi> and who ſhall hinder him from doing his pleaſure, for he will worke and <hi>who can let?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the word of the Lord came again unto me, ſaying, what ſeeſt thou now? and lo, I beheld a houſe by a great mountain, and there came one and removed this houſe and ſet it upon that great mountain as was by it; and I ſaw men and women come from Eaſt, Weſt, North and South to this houſe: and I ſaid, Lord, whoſe houſe is this? and my God and Father ſaid, it is my houſe, and the <hi>Sion</hi> ſpoken of in Scripture; and as you ſee it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by one and ſet upon the top of a great mountaine: it ſhewes that I the Lord of hoſt have removed ſorrow away from <hi>Sion</hi> by my owne power; and this mountain <hi>that you ſee the houſe ſet upon, is but the fulfilling of the</hi> Sciptures, <hi>that the Lords houſe ſhall be ſet above all mountaines:</hi> for this mountain which you ſee is ſet an, is the powers of the world; and by its being ſet on it, ſhewes that it is above them: above great mountaines, which are great men as have had the power, but now have not; and the mountaine being under it, it ſhewes that great men have not power over <hi>Sion</hi> as they have had, but are rather <hi>Sions</hi> foot-ſtoole, and ſo bend to the ſoles of Gods feet in <hi>Sion:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, is this houſe <hi>Sion,</hi> and the place that thy ſons and daughters ſhall come out of all Notions to? and the Lord ſaid, this is <hi>Sion,</hi> or it doth repreſent <hi>Sion;</hi> and by people coming to it out of all Countries; it ſhews, that I the Lord of hoſt, have people in all Countries: and this houſe doth onely ſhew, by ſtanding in a place as you ſee it doth, the place that my ſons and daughters ſhall make merry in: and where <hi>they meet together, if two or three of them, they ſhall be Sion; and they ſhall come to Sion with everlaſting joy upon their heads; and ſorrow ſhall flie away;</hi> for their going to <hi>Sion</hi> with joy and rejoycing, <hi>and their ſinging in the height of Sion,</hi> and <hi>making muſick as they go to Sion,</hi> is not their going
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:165764:25"/> to one place to worſhip, but they are glorying and rejoycing in me, becauſe thoſe that formerly were their enemies, are now <hi>cut down,</hi> ſo that they may ſpeak of me without any fear; <hi>for a Law ſhall go forth of Sion,</hi> which <hi>Sion</hi> is my Church, and the Law is my ſelf that they ſhall declare and ſpeak abroad: for all the enemies as Antichriſt and the beaſt, and the Whore, and forms and governments, and rules of men, being deſtroyed: there ſhall be now <hi>no other law then what ſhall come forth of Sion:</hi> I will now appear to be teacher, and Law, and rules, and worſhips, and all in all: and this <hi>Sion</hi> are my Church, or ſons and daughters unto whom I have made forth my ſelf; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared now by manifeſting my ſelf unto them, that I dwell in them, <hi>and am a Law in them: and unto this Sion ſhall people ſay, come let us go up to the houſe of the Lord, and he will teach us his wayes: &amp; the God of grace will be our teacher and inſtructer;</hi> and when he teaches us, <hi>we ſhall have no need of men to teach us: for he will write his Law in our hearts and in our inward parts, and we ſhall ſin no more:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, ſhall there be no Law or formes to walk by as hath been formerly? And the Lord ſaid, there ſhall be no other law but I my ſelf will be all the Law: and if any offend me, I my ſelf will terrifie him and not man: for I will be a <hi>terror to them that know not me,</hi> and a joy to them that know me: and when I have thus ſet my houſe <hi>upon the top of all mountains: then ſhall war ceaſe: and then ſhall ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts be taken out of men, and inſtead of them they ſhall have hearts of fleſh: and ſo I will ſaith the Lord, make men to beat their ſwords into Plouſheers, and their ſpears into pruning hookes; and the nation ſhall not learn War any more:</hi> for when I have taken the power from great men, and likewiſe their ſelf intereſt: <hi>that ſo he that laboured all the day and he that laboured but one hour in the vinyard,</hi> had both wages alike: ſo it ſhall be that they that have ſtrived for honour and greatneſs and have laid up baggs of Gold and Silver, for five, or two, or twenty, or thirty, fourty yeers together, ſhall have no more then he that hath not laid up any thing at all, or elſe hath laid up but a very little but in one yeer: and whereas he that had <hi>wrought in the heat of the day, did murmur and thought it harſh that he ſhould have no more then he that worketh but one hour:</hi> the Lord of the vinyard told him, <hi>it was his own he might chuſe whether he would give any thing or no:</hi> and what I do give thee I do it out of mine own free will: for all is mine ſaith the Lord of hoſts, all the beaſts of the field, and all the riches of the world is mine, and not thine; and though I have lent thee them: and thou
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:165764:26"/> having not made a right uſe of them, I take them from thee and give them to thy fellow creatures for their uſe as well as thine, for when thou hadeſt theſe things as I have now taken from thee, thou madſt them but inſtruments of cruelty to thy fellow creatures: <hi>and ſo did not uſe this world as if thou uſed it not, but uſed this world as if thou ſhouldeſt never part from it:</hi> but I have taken theſe things from thee that thou ſhouldeſt <hi>uſe this world as if thou uſed it not: for the faſhion of this world paſſeth away, and all things ſhall now become new:</hi> and theſe your Idols, of gold and ſilver, I will be ſuch a terror to you, that if you do not throw them away, ye ſhall be conſumed in my wrath. <hi>Now I ariſe to ſhake terribly the earth, and I will do this my act my ſtrange act:</hi> as to make the low and poor equal with the rich, that they may every one ſit under his own vine and none make him afraid: but all enjoying the fruits of the earth and ſo no longer to work for others, or others to have the benefit of their labours: but every man <hi>ſhall now enjoy the fruits of his own labour: and if any be ſervants it ſhall be thoſe that know not me, ſaith the Lord of hoſts. Thus will I ſtain the pride and glory of man, and will bring down the haughtineſs of menand will lay low the mountaines, and will exalt the vallies, and then both oppreſſors and oppreſſions ſhall ceaſe:</hi> that the creation may be reſtored from bondage: and this is the time of the reſtitution of all things, whom the heavens muſt retain: but the time being now come that the heavens cannot retain me any longer: therefore I come for to reſtore all things and the creature man from ſlavery and bondage, into the liberty of my ſons: that they may now no longer be in ſubjection to their fellow creatures; but ſhall now ſee themſelves to be equal with them: and the fat ſwine, to be but men whoſe breath is in their noſtrils: that I may appear to be all and in all: that ſo univerſal freedom may <hi>be in your ſtreets, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but peace within your borders; that righteouſneſs may now co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the earth,</hi> and the emnity of all creatures be taken away: that the ground may now <hi>be freed from the curſe; and the earth bring forth her increaſe,</hi> that I alone may be and none beſides me, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, who is the life of all creatures.</p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, <hi>Son of Man</hi> behold, behold, and loe, I looked and there appeared <hi>Chariots in Heaven runing up and down,</hi> and I told them, and there were ſeven of them, and one that led them about and was before them, cried with a loud voice to them that were in the Chariots, come let us go down and deſtroy the earth, before this yeer be at an end:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:165764:26"/> and I beheld that he that ſaid ſo, drew his ſword and gave it to a man; and ſaid: goe thou and do the worke of the Lord, <hi>and I will be with thee, and thou ſhalt prosper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I ſaid Lord, what meanes theſe Charriots, there being ſeven of them? and the Lord ſaid, the Charriots ſet forth thoſe whom I have appointed to do my worke; and there being ſeven of them, ſhewes a perfect and compleat number that ſhall accompliſh and do all my pleaſure: and one being before: ſhewes that I, the Lord of hoſt, have ſtirred them up and will lead them on and be with them: and as thou ſeeſt them in heaven; it ſhewes, that I have retained them in my favour: and one with them, it ſhews that I have been kept in heaven, until the time of the reſtitution of all things, or I have not made my name known: and whereas he cried come let us <hi>go down and deſtroy the earth before this year is at an end: it ſhewes the time of reſtitution is now at hand that I the Lord of hoſt, will reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my wooll and flax,</hi> my glory and honour; and I thus appearing; earthly powers, which robbed me, muſt be deſtroyed: and I ſaid, Lord, by earthly powers do you mean the Parliament? and by the year, do you mean, a year as we call it, as from <hi>Jan.</hi> to <hi>January?</hi> and the Lord ſaid, <hi>by the earth,</hi> is meant the Parliament which ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: and as he ſaid, <hi>before the year is at an end:</hi> is meant that the Parliament ſhall be deſtroyed and brought to nothing before <hi>January</hi> next; and ſo the year, to be a year as you account yeares: and ſome of them I will bring into me, to be in my <hi>favour, and others ſhall be devoured in my wroth: for I will make a ſhort worke on the earth:</hi> and as thou ſaweſt one that drew his ſword being before them, he doth repreſent me, and as he gave his ſword away to that man that ſtood by him, and ſaid, <hi>take this ſword and do my work.</hi> It ſhewes that I have made choice of a man to lead my Inſtruments on to do all my pleaſure: and <hi>whereas he gave him the ſword and bid him prosper:</hi> ſo I will, by my own power in you &amp; by you, effect my ſtrange work: and I ſaid, Lord, what man is this whom thou haſt given thy ſword to? and the Lord ſaid, it is him whom I have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and ſtirred up to do my worke, as I have allreadie decleared to you: and the ſet time or the Longeſt time of the being of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is but ſixe hundred threeſcore and ſix daies as I have ſhewn to thee allready,</p>
            <p>And the Lord within me that hath ſhewn me theſe things, told me that for the truth of what I had ſeen &amp; had reveal'd, as <hi>that the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament ſhould be brought to nothing in ſuch a ſhort time, he the Lord of</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:165764:27"/> 
               <hi>hoſt within</hi> me when he revealed it to me and commanded me to write it, and told me, as ſoon I had done writing of it, I ſhould be taken in a ſhaking fit: which proved very true: and it came upon me as ſoon as I had done writing of it, before I could ſpeake to them as was with me, or before I could riſe from the ſtoole I ſat on; in which fit of ſhaking, I was by a power taken off the ſtoole and lifted up; though one did ſtrive to hold me down: whereby I ſee it is the Lords time to confound all things beſides himſelf; that he may have the glory of all, and he onely be honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: unto which I ſay amen, amen.</p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying: behold, behold, what ſeeſt thou now? and loe! I beheld a buſh about ſeven foot high all on fire: and I ſaid, Lord, what meaneth this buſh to be of a flame and not to conſume? and the Lord ſaid, by this buſh, is ſet forth my people, and by the fire, is ſet ſorth I the Lord of hoſt; &amp; as the buſh was all on fire, ſo will I be a fire to my Church; as the buſh was not conſumed, but rather more freſher, ſo will I burne away the droſs and filthineſſe of my Church, and make them more pure then ever they were; and as the buſh ſtood ſtill: ſo will I by my burning away their filth, make them (the Church) ſtand ſtill and wait upon me, and ſo make them leave of running after any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teacher or outward meanes by which they have received ſome comforts, as from ſtreames: but will make them to come unto me, <hi>the fountain where they ſhall have their filland be ſatisfied: and as I did in old time appear to Moſes my ſervant in a burning buſh, ſo have I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared</hi> to thee now in a burning buſh: and as I ſent <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> to tell him <hi>I will have my people out of the Land, and ſo Redeem them from their bondage and ſlaverie,</hi> ſo my time is now at hand that I will Redeem my ſons and daughters <hi>from their heavie Task-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as the powers of this world: but as</hi> Pharoah <hi>was ſo envious againſt my people as to gather an army to follow them for to deſtroy them: ye read that inſtead</hi> of deſtroying my people, <hi>they were all drowned in the red Sea:</hi> even ſo all thoſe that will not grant my ſons and daughters freedome and libertie as to enjoy the fruits of the earth, that they may glorifie me: ſhall have their hearts hardned to war againſt them: <hi>but as I appeared for Moſes and the children of Iſrael and gave them deliverance,</hi> So will I now appear againſt all thoſe that appear againſt me the Lord of hoſt, or againſt my people: and will <hi>deſtroy them and conſume them that they may never</hi> be more: <hi>for I have spoken and it ſhall ſurely come to Paſſe; for I will do all my pleaſure ſaith the Lord</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:165764:27"/> 
               <hi>of hoſt.</hi> And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this man and ſee what he doth: and loe, I beheld a man in gay cloathes: and he had a bagge in his hand; and he put his other hand and tooke al the mony that was in it and threw it about ſo long as any was in it: and thus ſhall all Miſers in time throw away their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that they have horded up and bring it (their gold and ſilver) out of their cheſts, and baggs out of their places where they have laid them, ſaith the Lord of hoſt, for I will make them do it: <hi>that they that have gathered much may have none over: and they that have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered little may have no lack:</hi> ſaith the mighty God of <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And preſently after this: I ſaw the appearance of a man: his rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>was of all colours like a rain-bow,</hi> and it came down to his feet: and I looked and could ſee no ſeme upon it, for it was without <hi>ſeme, and he had on his head a Crown of gold, and in his right-hand a Scepter,</hi> and I ſaw him coming to me, and I cried out, in the name of the Lord of hoaſt come not to me: but he came to me, and told me, that he was <hi>Jeſus Chriſt; the mightie Angell of the Lord of hoaſt;</hi> and that he muſt come into me: and then he would declare unto me <hi>things that muſt ſhortly come to paſſe:</hi> for now the Lord of hoſt had done ſpeaking to the outward ears and appearing to the fleſhly eyes: and will deal inwardly; both appear and ſpeak to the ſpirituall eyes, &amp; he entred into me which made me tremble &amp; quake: and then I heard a voice within me, ſaying, <hi>harken to this noiſe that I will make,</hi> and I harkned: and loe it thundred, and I ſaid Lord, what is the meaning of this, and the Lord ſaid: theſe are the ſeven thunders that uttered their voices to <hi>John; and he would have writ the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them and I commanded him that he ſhould not,</hi> becauſe the meaning of them would have made my ſervants not to ſearch ſo much into this <hi>Revelations</hi> which were written by <hi>John?</hi> but now I will declare them unto thee: <hi>theſe ſeven thunders</hi> ſhew a perfection, or a compleating of my determination. Which I have ſet; before I will begin to take the powers from the earth, and the laſt of theſe thunders or all in one ſhall take effect according to my determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as I ſhewed it to my ſervant <hi>John)</hi> in the year one thouſand ſix hundred and fiftie, but I would not have him write it: though I have now commanded thee to write it; and that I will begin my worke in this year, as it was ſhewed to <hi>John</hi> in this Iland of <hi>England:</hi> and I will bring to nothing the Parliament: but will ſtirre up their hearts and the wicked to joyne with them againſt <hi>Fairfax,</hi> that ſo I may deſtroy them <hi>whom</hi> I <hi>have appointed for the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:165764:28"/> and ſo to be a terror and a dread to the others; and will make them be quiet.</p>
            <p>But preſently after this the word of the Lord came again unto me, ſaying, behold, this that I preſent to thee: and I looked and loe, a tree that had on it twelve ſorts of fruits, and the Lord ſaid, <hi>the fruit of this tree is for the healing of the Nations:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, what doth this tree repreſent? And my eternal God within me ſaid, it doth repreſent me the Lord of hoſts; I am the tree and onely that which can cure the Nations; and the fruits of me or of my work which I am now a doing;</p>
            <p>Is Firſt, to deſtroy earthly powers and ſo to bring down their ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I will make thoſe that have drawn their ſwords to make war (if they be not deſtroyed) beat their ſwords into plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheers, and their ſpears into pruning hooks.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I will be a terror to thoſe that have oppoſed me, that they ſhall be afraid of me; and inſtead of gathering themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as they have done: they ſhall <hi>hide themſelves in holes of the rocks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I will deſtroy ſelf-intereſt, that ſo there may be no ſtriving for riches.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, I will deſtroy ambition, that there ſhall be no ſtriving for honour.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, I will take away the pride of the heart, that there ſhall be none that ſhall think themſelves better then the reſt.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, I will take from man that preſumption, as to think to have one or two men to wait upon him.</p>
            <p>Eightly, I will make thoſe that have riches, give them to them that have none.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, I will make every man to be at peace one with the other.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, I will make all my ſons and daughters, <hi>to be of one heart and mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eleventhly, I will take away the curſe of the earth, that with a very little labour it ſhall bring forth its fruits.</p>
            <p>And Twelfthly, I will make that which one hath, to be ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that ſo the naked may be cloathed, and the hungry fed: and if any have any thing better then others, it ſhall be my ſons and daughters, for I will make all work in one way or other a little, for to keep themſelves out of want, ſaith I the Lord of hoſts; for I
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:165764:28"/> will take the curſe from off the earth, that the earth may be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and I will take the enmity from all creatures, that they may be at peace with each other: and I will make them <hi>to be fruitfull and multiply that they may be ſtrong to work</hi> and bring forth <hi>thouſands and ten thouſands,</hi> and ſo will make working a pleaſure and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that I may be glorified and have the honour, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, behold, behold, and loe, I looked and there appeared a river running up and down on the earth: And I ſaid, Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, what earth is this, and river that runs up and down thus? And my God ſaid, this is your body, and the bodies of my ſons and daughters, which the earth ſets forth; and the river is the river of life mentioned in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations;</hi> and this life is the pouring forth of my ſpirit upon this earth of men and women; and as you ſaw the living waters run about, it is that living waters, which are the fulneſs or flowings forth of my ſelf in ſuch a clear diſcovery and manifeſtation, as to over-power the earth man, with my glory as it is written, <hi>he that beleeveth on me,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>out of his belly ſhall flow forth rivers of living waters:</hi> which water of life proceedes from the throne of God; that is after my bright appearing, and filling my ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with my fulneſs, from them ſhall <hi>flow forth the water of life;</hi> that is, a diſcovery of me, or making me known to others, that I am the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> that I am <hi>all and in all;</hi> that I will now take the power into my own hands, and will be glorified: for my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are my throne, and the place where I dwell, ſaith the Lord of hoſts; and as there are <hi>three that bear record in heaven, the Father, Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one:</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> is the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> is the <hi>Father,</hi> and ſo I bear witneſs to them that have but a ſmal diſcovery of me; that is they living in ſome light, and ſo have ſome knowledge of me, they are ſaid to be witneſſes to his ſoul, even the <hi>Father, holy Ghoſt</hi> and <hi>Word,</hi> which is all but I the Lord of hoſts; witneſſing to them that I make forth my ſelf unto them that they are mine: <hi>and the three that bear record in earth, the Spirit, Water, and Bloud, and all agree in one;</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> is the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Water,</hi> the <hi>water of life mentioned,</hi> to <hi>proceed from the throne;</hi> and the <hi>Bloud,</hi> is the <hi>Bloud</hi> of I the Lord of hoſts; and ſo all theſe three <hi>that witneſs in the earth,</hi> which is the bodies of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to whom I have made forth my ſelf, is I the Lord of hoſts, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that I am theirs, and ſo ſealing them up to be mine; and thoſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:165764:29"/> whom I have, and will make <hi>the water of life</hi> to run from them: that is my ſelf ſo to over-power them, that I may appear to be <hi>all and in all,</hi> and ſo will I have the glory, ſaith the Lord of hoſts; for the time is now at hand theſe Scriptures ſhall be fulfilled, and there ſhall be no more curſe; there ſhall not be any wicked fleſh or ſin that ſhall hinder my ſervants from the injoyment of me, ſaith I the Lord of hoſts, <hi>but the throne of God and of the Lamb ſhall be in it:</hi> There ſhall be no power to rule and domineer in my City where I rule, which Citie is my ſons and daughters, but I will be all in them, and they ſhall ſee my face, and my name ſhall be in their foreheads: I will ſpeak in them and manifeſt my glory in them, which ſhall be as a mark on their foreheads, that they are the ſeed which I the Lord of hoſts have bleſſed; <hi>and there ſhall be no night there:</hi> they ſhall have no need of a candle, <hi>neither the light of the Sun;</hi> that is, my ſons and daughters ſhall have no need of any outward adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ordinances, or wayes of worſhips which they have had, but my river of life (running in them, that is my ſelf dwelling in them) ſhall give them life and make them to reign over <hi>ſin, hell,</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> and all <hi>enemies; ſo they ſhall reign with me for ever,</hi> ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, behold, behold, that which I will now ſhew thee; and lo, I beheld one with a vail over his face ſo that none could ſee his beauty, but onely ſome glimmering light of him: and I ſaid, Lord, who doth this ſet forth that his face hath a vail over it, that his beauty cannot be ſeen? And my eternal God, ſaid, this ſets forth me the eternal King of Glory, who have hid my glory and beauty from the children of men, and alſo from them who have been my deareſt ſervants; that they have ſeen but very little of my beauty and alſo I have been ſilent and have not made out my ſelf in any full meaſure or diſcovery of my ſelf as yet: but as you ſaw him throw away his vail, and did behold him in his beauty: ſo will I now make out my ſelf in the fulneſs of my ſelf to my ſons and daughters that they may now ſee and behold my beauty and the glory of me, that they may no longer go a whoring after other Gods: but that I the King of glory might have them come running to me to be taught by me, the Lord of hoſts, who am the King of glory.</p>
            <p>And again the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, behold, and obſerve, and I will ſhew thee that which ſhall ſuddenly come
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:165764:29"/> to paſs: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, I looked and there appeared a man with a ſword in his hand ready drawn; ſaying, <hi>I am now come to cut down that time may be no longer: I have a long time been ſilent, but I am now riſen like a man of warre, and will cut down and devoure at once.</hi> And I beheld: and preſently he fell to cutting off the heads of men that were together: and then he ſaid, I will not onely cut off the heads, but I will cut up the root too; that there may not be left root nor branch. And I ſaid, Lord, who doth this man repreſent? and my God ſaid, it repreſents me the Lord of hoſt who am now riſen to cut down and deſtroy all my enemies: I have along time bin ſilent, but I will no longer be ſo: for my time is now come that I may make a ſhort work: and I ſaid, Lord, what doth time mean as he ſaid, it ſhould be no longer? and the Lord ſaid, by time is meant the ſet time of my determination which is now in this yeare 1650. but the meaning of time ſhall be no longer, <hi>and time, times, and dividing of times, in</hi> Daniel, <hi>and the forty and two months</hi> ſpoken of, are now in this year 50. a beginning to be accompliſhed in this Land, to the cutting down of the Parliament and all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers beſides my ſelf in this Land, as was ſhewed thee by the cutting off of heads with my ſword: and as he ſaid he will cut down the roots too; and he thruſt the ſword as he had in his hand into the earth, and did cut off the roots, and ſaid, he will neither leave root nor branch, but I will cut off the Parliament and all the powers here in <hi>England</hi> firſt, and they ſhall never riſe more on the earth: the roots being cut up, it ſhews the Parliament who are a power choſen by earthly men, ſhall in this year be cut down, and there ſhall never be any more power; but I will be the power that ſhall rule here, ſaith the Lord of Hoſt: And after I had writ this, I heard a voice within me, ſaying, <hi>I will ſhake thee that thou maiſt know it ſhall come to paſſe,</hi> and that I have commanded thee to write and print this ſaith the Lord of hoſt, who will be all and in all: and I was preſently taken with ſhaking, ſo that I was not able to hold my ſelf ſtill.</p>
            <p>And the word of my God came again, ſaying, Behold, and I will ſhew thee thoſe things that ſhall come to paſſe, and lo, there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to me a field of Corn, and Reapers, with their ſickles ready to reap it downe; and preſently, I heard a voice ſay, the harveſt is ripe, cut it down: And I ſaid, Lord, what doth his field hold
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:165764:30"/> forth? and the Lord ſaid, the Parliament and all earthly powers: and the harveſt, ſhews the time appointed that they are now ripe for the ſlaughter: for thruſt in the cickle the harveſt is ripe: this harveſt ſets forth that I had a ſet time for earthly powers to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue before I would deſtroy them: but the harveſt is now ripe, in this year 1650. Therefore as you ſaw theſe reapers cut down the wheat, and made the others ſtand bowing and bending; they repreſent my inſtruments being ſeven; ſhews they are a perfect number, which I have choſen in this yeer, now the time of the harveſt being come: that they ſhall cut down and deſtroy all powers whom I have appointed for the ſlaughter, and make the reſt ſtand bowing to me in my ſons and daughters, who am <hi>the mighty God of Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Lord ſpake again unto me, ſaying: behold, behold, and loe: I beheld a beaſt with one horn puſh down men and kept them under, and ſome he killed of them. And I ſaid Lord, what doth this beaſt mean? This beaſt is the powers (ſaith the Lord) as I have already told thee: the men are my Saints, which he hath puſhed down and kept under, as the men that did appear firm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt oppreſſion and cruelty: and as he the beaſt killed ſome: ſo have the Powers killed ſome as <hi>Locker</hi> and <hi>Thomſon;</hi> but as you ſaw ſome antient men come together, the antient men, are they that are mentioned in <hi>Daniel,</hi> that are called <hi>the antient of dayes:</hi> which is onely a ſet time for this beaſt to puſh down the Saints and to keep them under; which time is now at an end in this yeer one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty: and theſe antient men all in white, are my ſervants, that judge this beaſt to burned; or I appearing in them, to cauſe them to give judgement againſt this beaſt; and in giving judgment againſt him, you ſaw one cut off his head and burning his body; which doth ſhew that <hi>the ancient of dayes</hi> is now come, and that my ſet time for him to have power is at an end; therefore I the Lord of hoſt will now ariſe and deſtroy the powers and bring them to nothing before the yeer one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty one, and burn them, that no other power beſides my ſelf may be.</p>
            <p>And the word of the moſt high God came unto me, ſaying, behold, behold, and loe, I beheld, and there appeared one like a man, and alſo there was a picture of a man whoſe head was
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:165764:30"/> 
               <hi>gold, breaſt ſilver, thighes braſs, and feet, part iron and part clay,</hi> and I beheld till the man break in peices the Image and ſtamped it under his feet: and I ſaid Lord who doth this man ſet forth? and the Lord ſaid it ſets forth I the Lord of hoſts: and this Image ſets forth all powers, as the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Emperours, and Kings, and Parliaments, and as the man brake in peices the Image: ſo will I the Lord of hoſts, break in peices all the powers and bring them to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for the time is now come that I will <hi>cut the ſtone out of the mountain,</hi> which ſtone is my inſtrument which I have choſen to cut down and break in peices all other mountains, the inſtrument which I have choſen and cut out of this mountain (which ſhall be broken to peices) is <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and thoſe whom I ſhall ſtir up to be with him: and the mountain is this power that is now on foot in the land, which ſhall be deſtroyed; for I the Lord of hoſts, have purpoſed it, and it ſhall come to paſs.</p>
            <p>Having received thoſe things and written them down; about two dayes after I alſo received a command to go to <hi>London</hi> and put them in Print, for they muſt ſhortly come to paſs; and I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with this command received this <hi>motto, that I ſhould have no reſt until that I did get them printed;</hi> but that I might know that the Lord of hoſts, by whom all creatures are made, hath now command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and hath appeared to me and that they ſhall come to paſs, I ſhall be exceedingly terrified; at which preſent I had ſome thing (which was told me it was bread of life) thruſt as I thought into my mouth, which was told me ſhould be bitter in my belly; and in truth I had a bitter fit of ſhaking and trembling, and in my belly an extraordinary working, ſo that I have had but little reſt: but as I ſaw the appearance of a man which told me that he was now come to tell me what I ſhould do; and as he had a ſword in his hand, ſo me thought I ſaw the ſame appearance terrifying <hi>me,</hi> and telling <hi>me</hi> I ſhall have no reſt until I doe it: which through abundance of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſorrow of minde; as I have now for two dayes under-gone) the third night I had ſome muſick which was very pleaſant: and afterwards the word of the Lord came unto me, ſaying, behold, and there appeared a company of women dancing and ſinging; I ſaid, Lord what doth theſe mean to dance and ſing thus? And did alſo throw away their money: and my God told me, that as I ſaw them ſing and dance and throw away their money; ſo before
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:165764:31"/> the firſt of January next ſhall all my ſonnes and daughters ſing and rejoyce, for joy, and throw away their money, <hi>as you ſaw them</hi> throw away theirs, and ſo ſhall it be in that time that <hi>men ſhall uſe the world as if they uſe it not:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, ſhall it be before the Parliament be deſtroyed? and the Lord ſaid, the Parliament ſhall be deſtroyed firſt. And I ſaid, Lord, ſhall there be no power, and ſo no law? and my God ſaid, there ſhall be no power beſides my ſelf, ſo no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther law: but I will be a power and a law to keep the wicked under; and if any have any power, it ſhall be my ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; for they ſhall have of the beſt, and ſhall reigne as Kings: but not as to uſurpe any authority over the reſt: but I will make the reſt come bowing and bending to them, and be afraid of me the Lord of hoſt in them, and ſo will make men to care for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but for things that are neceſſary; as for riches, they ſhall not ſtrive after it: and then I ſaid, Lord, the men will be idle if they may have it for fetching it, as cloaths and victuals, and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries: but the Lord ſaid, that he would make all men worke as to provide things neceſſary for them: but I will take the curſe of their labours away; and then their labours ſhall he pleaſanter to them then ever they have been: but as for drunkards and ſuch as have waſted my creatures, in vain, <hi>There ſhall no longer be any ſuch: but I will be ſuch a terror to the wicked that they ſhal be afraid of me; and ſhall howl for ſorrow and grief, when my ſons ſhall ſing and rejoyce for joy;</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, is this all their torment as they ſhall have? and my God, ſaid, will not this be torment enough to be caſt out of my love and favour, and ſo to lie under my wrath, I plaguing of them for their wickedneſſe, and making them ſervants to my ſonnes and daughters; yea, they ſhall think it happy to doe any thing for them: but I ſaid, Lord, it is ſaid, that <hi>in the laſt day the wicked ſhall receive this ſentence, goe you curſed into everlaſting fire;</hi> and the Lord ſaid, that this fire is his wrath, which the wicked ſhal be thrown under, and he will be as fire in their bones which ſhal burn them: and I ſaid, Lord, is there no hell for them to be thrown in? and my God ſaid, all the hell is, they ſhall be caſt out of my love and favour, and ſo in ſtead of enjoying me they ſhall be terrified by me; which hell ſhall be here on earth, for when my ſons and daughters <hi>ſhall ſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, they ſhall howl and weep for ſorrow:</hi> and I ſaid, Lord, it is ſaid, that thou wilt <hi>ſeparate the ſheep from the Goats; and ſet one on the</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:165764:31"/> 
               <hi>right hand and the other on the left hand, &amp; that in the world to come:</hi> And the Lord ſaid, I will make a ſeperation, and ſuch a ſeper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation as is ſpoken of; and that I will now ſet the one, of my ſons and daughters on my right hand, which is my love and favour to them: and the other; to wit the wicked, ſhall bee on my left hand: that is under my wrath: and I ſaid Lord, what is become of the wicked that have ceaſed: if there be no hel nor no other life? and the Lord ſaid, their bodyes are returned to earth from whence they came, and ſo ſhall ever be, and never be more: but their ſpirits as ſoon as they go out of their bodies being not made of the four Elements as fire, water, earth and aire; neither is it the ſoule, which is their life: for I the Lord is their life and ſoule: and ſo ſoone as I draw my ſelf, which is the ſoul out of the body, the body returnes to the earth and there it continues: but the ſoul, which is the life of the body, which life is my own inviſible being returnes to its centre, as the body doth to his, and there remaines; which centre I the Lord of hoſt am: and ſo the ſoul which is the life cannot ſuffer any torment after it is out of the body: but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes to me to be at reſt with me: but the ſpirit, and the ſoul being two diſtinct, the ſpirit of a man, it is that is and ſhall be tormented. When the body ſhall reſt and the ſoul be alſo at reſt: I meane the body of him that is deceaſed, when his ſpirit (which is his conſcience, that is compounded of reaſon, wiſedome and knowledge, and ſo proceeds from man) and is called the ſpirit of a man: ſhall be tormented for ever, and that in a body, though it be not in the ſame body; for this ſpirit which is compounded of reaſon, wiſdome, and knowledge, is that which exalts and ſets it ſelf againſt God; and ſo is the utter enemy to God; it being ſome thing which proceeds from fleſh, and proceeds out of man, and yet it is not fleſh nor man: and as ſoon as it comes out of one man where I the God of gods doe not rule, it goes into another wicked man, and there acts the ſame things which it did in the firſt; and ſo as <hi>Cain</hi> killed <hi>Abel,</hi> the ſame ſpirit is in wicked men, killing the Saints: which ſpirit of man being all that ſhall be tormented, I ſuffer it to embody it ſelf in man, untill it becomes a legion of Devils; and there they remain in man, untill I by my ſpirit caſt them out: or till I withdraw my ſelf, and ſo let the body goe from whence it comes: and ſo the Devil which my Sonne Chriſt caſt out
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:165764:32"/> of the man, which man was tormented by it, it being in him (for ſo long as it was in him it did keep him from enjoying me) and ſo did torment him; is the ſpirits of wicked men transfuſed into one, and ſo rules in a man: and as it ſpake and deſired Chriſt to let it go into the <hi>herd of ſwine,</hi> it ſhewes, that it was not able to a bide in that place were I would not have him tarry: neither can it go into any, but to thoſe that I give it a commiſſion to go into, and as it choſe to go into ſwine; the ſwine ſets forth wicked men: ſo that the Devil that was caſt forth &amp; went into the herd of ſwine, went into wicked men: and as the ſwine ran into the Sea and were drovvned; ſo thoſe into whom I do ſuffer the ſpirit of a wicked man to go into and remaine and not caſt it out, that man is tormented by that ſpirit and drowned in a Sea of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. But as the ſpirit cried out, <hi>art thou come to torment me before my time?</hi> it ſhewes, that a ſpirit is not capable of torment out of a body, but in a body: which bodies ſhall now be, that the ſpirits of all wicked men ſhall be tormented in, and they ſhall for ever as one Devil and his Angels, be burning in my wrath; that is, thoſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men that remaine, ſhall be the places wherein all the ſpirits of wicked men, and their ſpirits ſhall be tormented day and night; that is in bodies, wherein nothing but wickedneſſe dwels: ſo that all might be tormented and deſtroyed, but I the Lord of hoſt: and I ſaid Lord, there are ſome things in likeneſſe of hens, or doggs, or any any thing elſe, that can ſpeake: and my God ſaid that theſe are the ſpirits of wicked men: whom I can make in any ſhape, and can give them power to ſpeake to other wicked men, or their ſpirits in them: which ſpirit <hi>workes in the children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> in this forme and ſhape: and ſo theſe ſpirits are witches ſo called: becauſe I ſuffer them in whom they remaine to have power, and ſo to bewitch them, that they come not to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of me: that is thoſe in whom this power of darkneſſe rules, are ſo overpowred with darkneſſe, that they become fit ſubjects or bodies for me to execute my wrath upon them: which bodies being ſenſible of me the Lord, and of the glory, and happineſſe of my ſons and daughters, <hi>ſhal gnaw their tongues for paine,</hi> even in this world: ſo that the reſurrection in Scripture mentioned is not a reſurrection of the body out of the earth: but a reſurrection of the the body from darkneſſ to light, and from the wrath of me, to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:165764:32"/> the love and favour of me. For ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I am the reſurrection and the life:</hi> ſo that the reſurrection and life is Chriſt: that is ſo to be raiſed from <hi>the body of death and ſin as to be anointed with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God:</hi> and ſo to become new being dead before, and now to be alive, <hi>and ever to be with God.</hi> Free from apprehending God to be angry with us: but always feeling his divine power ruling in us and cauſing of us to ſee and look upon him as one that is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
